And, uh, hello everyone.
Today we will have a tutorial
for the digital bodies, uh, week.
And, uh, we will navigate into different, uh, software.
Uh, firstly, um, I hope that you enjoyed the lecture
of yesterday, but I also wanted to, uh, tell you that
the software that we are using today is not software that,
uh, is thought for pattern making.
It's not like the cloth, really,
because some people were asking this make human is like
cloth, really no make human, uh, is a software just
for character creation used mainly
for from animators.
And then there is a blender add on
where you can have clothes, uh,
and, uh, animate the figures.
Um, and then, um,
the objective is that if you are able
to follow this tutorial, uh, today, normally by the end
of the tutorial, you will already have something ready
to laser cut, meaning that you will have gone
through the whole process.
So, uh, you will, uh, mainly if you want,
you can just go directly, laser cut
and your assignment is done,
and then you only need to do the scanning.
Now, of course, uh, you could do this
as a, as a test.
And, uh, we also want to, uh, say that two, two
or more three things because they arose as questions.
You don't necessarily need to scan or model a human.
When we say digital bodies,
the bodies is like the body of knowledge.
Uh, so it's not only a body or a human body.
We, uh, talk always in fabric academy about human
and more than human.
So objects can be also bodies
or, uh, other, uh, animals or plants.
Uh, so, uh, it is not necessary
that you do a body.
We do the bodies. Uh,
the reason why I started doing the bodies was
because I needed mannequins for the exhibitions.
So, uh,
and probably you don't have a mannequin to do like some
prototyping on the labs.
Then you will also want to have some mannequin, uh, made.
Then it is not necessary that you do a one-to-one scale.
You can do a half scale,
or you can do a part of, you know, you can do only a hand
or, um, I remember yesterday there was, um,
uh, Annabel that she was showing the glasses.
And I say, that's great for the, you can do like a pair
of glasses, uh, for,
or a hat, you know, so you can also, uh,
work on, on that.
It does, it, it is not required that you fabricate
the thing that you scan.
So maybe you scan something,
but you fabricate something that you may digitally.
So all of these may be were your questions about the,
the week, and you can use many different materials.
Uh, for example, Patricia was saying, I would like not
to buy anything I want to recycle.
So you will have different boards.
You will need to do the placing of the pieces,
and you can have something
that has different materials in the same object.
It is not a problem as well.
Um, so I will be very, uh, quick,
uh, make human, uh, I hope that you were all able to
install it and I
will share my screen.
Um, now,
okay, Uhhuh, gimme a second
to accept, uh, some more
people that they are joining.
Or Claudia, if you can accept.
Yeah, if you will be accepting, then I will. Yeah.
Alright. So I hope that you were able to, um,
to download the make human
and that you can see my screen now.
We can do,
we can go.
Let me, yeah.
Okay, let me close it
and I will open it again so that
you can, uh, see.
Hmm. It doesn't close it. Yes.
Okay, so make human
In the meantime, I can close the Rhino Rico.
I can proudly say that I did my first blended tutorial today
to learn how to do the, the bullion operations.
And it was very easy. Nothing compared to Rhino.
Um, it was very easy.
So make human opens with a sample human.
You can, uh, zoom
and you can, uh, scroll with a, with a mouse
or with a mouse, but also in, uh, with the left click
and the control and the shift.
So try to work with how it works in the panning
and scrolling and zooming.
And then very, very easily you can, um,
see here all of the things that you can define.
So first we can define the gender.
I will make a male.
And here on the bottom, on the bottom left,
you see male age, muscle, weight, and height.
So this, it, he, it will be, uh,
46-year-old normal muscle.
The way the weight it is with percentage,
I will make somebody that is a little bit like that
and the height is one 70 centimeter.
So it'll be a little bit taller, maybe
not two meters and seven,
but, um, one 90
I, okay, we can make African,
it has like mixes also Asian, African,
and here.
Now you have a very simple, if I want,
I can convert this to a female just
because I want to show you that, uh,
in the body shapes you have more parameters for a female.
Like the, how it is more
or less the, the shape,
but you also have the gender
and you can work on, on the, on the breast, you can work
very detailed, but in the
male then, for example,
you can still work on that.
Let's see. And then the gender here,
it'll also work,
but not really in the, since the male doesn't have
so much breast, then you can, uh, go
and focus on the face.
So difficult for my mouse,
but it's like this.
And what we want is that, uh, for example, I want,
uh, a little bit like this,
and yeah, I don't want to play with, uh, all of those.
But on the right side here, you can go
really into detail, like forehead, uh,
eyebrows, neck, you see,
let's say forehead.
I want the forehead
to be smaller.
Mm.
And of course, I need to rotate it to see from all sides
or this thing, no, and mouth details.
So maybe it's smiling
or maybe it has the lips bigger.
So you can really go into detailing
every little piece of, uh, you can go
for the torso.
So basically what you do is that you go through all of those
and you don't really need to, uh, adjust them all.
Uh, you can even use them like that. Yeah. Okay.
Um, you can go in the details of the hands,
and then you have right hand, left hand, right foot,
left foot, left shoulder.
For example, if there is a mass of the muscles,
uh, the arm and the legs, uh, you don't want
to do the random because the randomized,
it will just random, uh, delete everything
that you've done before.
But what you want to do, for example, and what you can do,
and this is very hard hemp helpful, is
that you could eventually be taking measurements, uh,
from, uh, from a real person
and that you can insert those, um, in, uh, make human.
And that's the nice part of make human.
So I can measure my neck sin conference, the neck height,
Uh, I will make it very tall.
Actually, I want to make it very tall because the neck,
because, uh, I will not
fabricate the head for the mannequin.
So I want to cut it.
Um, and you can,
here you have the measurements of the neck, then you have
the arm measurements,
and you will see that when you play with the slide there,
it shows you which circumference it'll, uh,
it'll give you, then you have the torso.
So it is as if you are doing the tailoring, uh,
let's say waist circumference.
Let's make it bigger.
I, And then
after you have played with all of the, the hips and the leg
and the knee, everything, uh, you can go
into, you can export that directly.
So what we will do is that we will press this button,
which is like a disc, uh,
and here you will give, you will get the,
the different, uh, export options, uh,
what you want to work with.
Uh, I mean, you can export, you can save it now as,
uh, uh, make human file.
And then you can, uh, export in different ways.
Um, I can export
as OBG Newman.
And here, if you click the three dots, it tells you
where it saves it.
In my case, uh, I, I save most
of the things in the downloads.
So, but, um, you can also make your folder
and be more neat.
And also, you normally I export in OBG
and in SDL, these are the two, let's say, standard.
Um, then here you need to choose
if you, which is the scale.
So for example, I should have chosen centimeter,
so I will override it.
And you know that you've saved this on this scale.
So when you import it in another software, you know,
if you have to scale it up or not, or you know, which,
because this is in a real scale, it's like one meter
and 900 centimeters.
Now this would be the minimum, uh, so
that you can do different manipulations on this, um,
on this, uh, body.
But, uh, we can go further, uh,
in the main, uh,
and we can also, if you, if you want,
we can dress this, uh, person.
So we can put a hat
and we can put, uh, clothes
and different geometries.
And the good thing about, so shoes.
So shoes, yes.
The good thing about, uh, make Human is
that there is a huge community,
and the community is making more.
These are only the sample ones,
but you can, uh, download, uh, things from the community.
And I will show you where now in the material
we have already chosen,
but you can be a little bit more
precise, for example.
And you see also here, there are more, uh, filters
and the eyes.
We can have the color of the eyes.
And here is the nice part.
So, uh, here, impose animate,
because I, this software is about
making animations
and, uh, anime having characters for animation.
So what you have is that you have also, if you want
to make an animation in blender, what you can do is
that you can choose a skeleton.
So each of the parts of the skeleton are the ones
that they are being animated.
So this one is a default one, for example,
or for the game engine.
Uh, but in, in my case, now, I will not, um, uh, animate.
But you can also choose a pose.
And that's also something nice
because you have many different poses.
For example, uh, here
you have different poses.
Uh, I was looking like, uh, in making the mannequins
for the exhibition this year.
So I really needed to have some standing poses,
very simple ones.
Um, so I downloaded those from the community.
And, but what we would like to do is that in the end,
on our case, we are going to, uh, slice
and cut this, uh, object.
So the best, uh, pose, let's say, would be something
that it has the hands open,
because I, I don't want to fabricate the hands,
I want to cut them out.
So this is the, the non pose.
And let's say we can do this one also is nice.
Um, the sitting pose, the running pose,
T pose, yeah, let's do this pose.
And then you can, uh, have expressions.
So here you can have somebody that is angry,
or it is, let me just, oh, oh,
sometime my mouse doesn't work very well.
It's so doubt
and well in, I would prefer
to have someone that has the mouth, uh, closed.
No, this one is not closed.
Um, so
maybe this one, I would have somebody
that has the mouth closed,
because sometimes it may human, when the mouth is open,
like in, normally you have a cavity.
It's for the animation, uh,
uh, characters.
And then you can also, uh, go to different settings.
So it doesn't really matter here,
but again, now that I have my, uh, model,
I can export Newman two in STL in
centimeters, and on my downloads.
So exports, and it writes it.
And this is the very, very easy part of a make human.
Uh, it is very nice.
And I mean, if you add the skeleton and ate it.
Now, um, I wanted to, um, go
into something that is quite, uh, easy,
but it can be also, uh, nice to explore.
I was, uh, yes, I was, um, trying
to find some, I was trying to find some
online mesh editor,
and I found this, uh,
there is Kiri Moto, but there is also this me editor.
Just let me
close the rhino.
Yeah, close. Mm-hmm.
So I found this, um, editor.
It's called Hyper 3D ai,
and it does different things, uh, on online,
on the browser,
so you can remix images, uh, you can
generate textures.
Uh, but I wanted to use this mesh editor.
This is very similar to a software that is called
Sculpt Trees that you can download also
on, on your computer.
Uh, there is something in the chat.
Best post, okay, tpo, uh, let,
let me know if, um, there is something
that I should look in the chat
because I, yeah, I cannot see it now.
Um, so mesh editor, you click import.
Let's see.
And I go to downloads.
And here I have
my new man.
Let's see.
I hope it will open it.
Well, while it opened it, uh,
do you have any questions about Make Human,
were you all able to open it?
Um, no. I guess everything is good.
Uh, I have it open. Uh, yeah. Okay.
It's, I was sure how I did it.
Okay, so this, uh, is, uh, open now.
And let's say I want to, uh, play with this.
I want to sculpt on it.
So very as if you were doing clay,
you can take a brush
and you can start like sculpting the,
eh, but it's good if you choose, for example,
the symmetry.
So I do all, like, whatever I do on the left is done.
Also on the right here, I can play with it intensity.
So let's say I want to do something that is like this,
but at the same time it needs to go all the way to the back.
Mm-hmm. And you can
inflate it large.
Let's see, uh, how it's this up.
And then what happens here is
that it gets like a little bit messy.
So what you want to do is that you want to choose the
smoothing tool and smooth it out so
that it is not like edgy very much.
And yeah, here, for example, I would like to smooth
that a little bit.
Yeah. And you can choose the intensity
and the radius of the smoothing.
Let's play a little bit more with the brush.
What I want here and here,
Let's see.
And,
and then you can increase the, the middles if you want.
And let's say that we like that, like this, um,
or whatever you've done.
Actually, I've done one
before, so that's the one
that I was working on.
So you can use the, the crease, the flatten, the smooth,
and the intensity and the radius with the symmetry.
And then after you can download that s an OBG.
Now what's, uh, what happens is that this mesh
is a mesh that maybe it's, you know,
it's topology, the points
and the triangulation is maybe a little bit distorted,
because I used the distortion.
And what I did afterwards is that I went to, uh,
the very nice, uh, polygonal app online,
uh, editor, and I opened
my, let's see.
Mm, let's, for example, yeah,
this one, we open it.
And you see here that the mesh is, uh,
more dense in some places than other places.
No. So here you have different, like only mesh,
um, commands.
And, uh, what I wanted to, uh, do is
that I wanted to do a remesh, a uniform remesh.
So you see now that everything is done uniformly.
Uh, you can also try, like, if you want
to use more smoothing or su subdivision,
but now your mess is clean, uh, and re meshed.
So Rico can take it and he can continue from here.
So, uh, just overview.
We worked with Make Human First, and then,
because I wanted to sculpt on the,
on the Human I made, I used this
Hyper 3D on browser sculpting.
But there is also, if you want to download,
there is sculptors, uh, software, if you want
to download the software, there is the sculptors.
It's exactly the same, like the hyper.
It's a little bit better actually.
Uh, hybrid three Ds on the browser.
And then when I just wanted to manipulate, uh, the
mesh topology, I open this Polygonal app,
and now Rico can continue with the blender.
Okay, great. Good afternoon, morning,
evening, wherever you are.
I hope you are well. Uh, does your brain hurt yet?
I've got, I've got more pain for you coming.
Um, how many, uh, I, uh, get ready to give me a thumbs up
or a question mark or whatever.
How many of you have tried using Blender in the past?
Okay, that's one. A few people. Okay, great.
And, uh, how many of you believe
that you're competent with Blender?
Jesse is good. Giselle is good. Giselle is laughing.
Giselle is, okay. So Jesse's good. All right.
So for the, for the rest of you who, uh, have, uh,
Patricia is a thumbs down.
All right, we're gonna, we're gonna
hopefully try to fix that today.
Um, can, can I ask for those of you
who gave me the initial thumbs up
that you've touched Blender,
but did not give a thumbs up when I asked you if you felt
competent with it, why, why,
why are you not comfortable with Blender?
Uh, you can type it in the chat, or you can unmute
and let me know and talk to me so I don't feel
so lonely here in Japan in the evening in the dark.
Can I go? Yeah.
Uh, the interface, it's a little overwhelming.
Okay. That, that's a
Common many panels.
We don't know what's happening there.
I know, I know.
And you're afraid to touch a button
'cause it might blow up your computer, right?
So, okay. Anybody else?
And I use it in, can you hear me?
Yes, I can. Martina.
Okay. I used it like 10 years ago in, uh, the university,
and then I didn't touch it anymore.
So that's the reason why I'm not confident,
let's say using it.
Okay, well, good news.
Martina Blender 10 years ago was a nightmare,
and it has gotten astronomically better in terms of, uh,
usability, um, uh, features, so on and so forth.
So I think hopefully today you're gonna be like, wow,
you're learning a completely new software.
Okay? This is the, the good news
and the bad news with Blender.
'cause it's an open source software, uh,
and a very well loved
and well, uh, supported open source for, uh, open source,
open source software is that it changes quickly.
I think, uh, I just watched the Blender conference in
Amsterdam that took place this past week,
and they said that, that in 2025 alone,
there were three revisions of this software,
and every time it got meaningfully better, okay?
Uh, blender Donut victim. Oh, Diana, I'm sorry about that.
I, I, um, now I'm curious to see what your donut looks like.
Okay. So with that, let me share my screen.
Uh, for, for those of you who have not received
or were aware that I created a, um,
a notion page to contain all of the notes
for today's session, let me go ahead and take that link
and drop it in the chat now so you can have that.
Uh, I'm going to go fast.
I'm not gonna stop and, and answer questions.
And, uh, this is being recorded
so you can watch it later at your own time and, and go slow.
I will do my best to not go too fast, that,
that I completely lose all of you.
Uh, but, um, the idea today is in that I'm going to wait
and make sure everybody catches up Okay.
With that, let me share the screen.
All right. Uh, there are going to be, oops, what is this?
This gets to go, uh, there are going to be two sessions, uh,
of the blender, uh, workshops I'm gonna do.
So today's gonna be one.
And then I think in about a month, I'm gonna follow up
with a, uh, second workshop.
Um, so this image here that you see is, is a, uh, cowboy
that I modeled from scratch on blender and rendered
and, and, uh, shown.
So if I, I'll try to zoom in here.
I mean, it's, oh, nope, I guess it doesn't work.
But anyway, uh, so modeling a human figure from scratch
without using, uh, make human
or any of those other tools is what I'm going to try
to get you close to being able to do.
Okay? Alright.
So before we get on with Blender, uh, blender,
as Jess all describes, feels like this
to most people, right?
Like, you look at it
and you just freak out with, with the amount of things
that you might have to, um, uh, deal with.
Let me tell you right now that in order for you to
be able to use Blender, in order for you to enjoy Blender,
you need to just relax, okay?
For this week in particular, you do not try to set any goals
that I'm going to be able to make
that cowboy like what Ricoh made.
I want you to be able to make a torso, a simple torso,
or just be able to just manipulate shapes, okay?
Your aim low for this week,
and just try to have as much fun as possible.
I'm going to walk you through the software,
and my objective for this week is, uh, well, first of all,
uh, blender can do many, many, many things,
and I'll, I'll, I'll show you that a little bit later.
Blender can be intimidating.
I've mentioned that, uh, you guys have told me that already.
You will not become a Blender expert today,
but hopefully you will no longer Fear Blender today.
All right? So with that, take a deep breath, set your mind
to, uh, ready to discover something beautiful.
And let's blend. All right, so what can, oh, oops,
I need to update this page.
Sorry. I have a,
I found this video online, which is 12 minutes long, that
that will show you everything that Blender can do.
Uh, I am going to actually play some of this, uh, I need
to reshare and make sure I have sound apologies for that.
Share, share, sound share. Okay, let's do this again.
Blender is is one
of the most feature packed 3D packages
you can find on the internet.
If you wanted, you could make a full length cartoon movie
from start to finish without ever leaving Blender.
But how would you do that? Well,
that's the question we're gonna talk about.
Let's look at all the blender
features you should know about.
Let's start with the more exciting
and lesser known features.
Before we jump to familiar ones,
like Modeling and Sculpting.
Blender has a video editing workspace that is as powerful
as dedicated suites like Premier Pro.
It includes audio mixing, syncing, scrubbing, scenes, masks,
effects, speed control, adjustment, layers,
transitions, and more.
Okay, so I'm not gonna play the rest of this video.
Uh, I, the link is here in my notes so
that you can watch it in full later.
But the point here is that this free software
basically turn you into a one person powerhouse
of digital content creation.
Uh, so, um, it is too much to learn in,
in one session.
Too much to learn. I, I could say in one lifetime.
Uh, so you kind of need to pick,
we're not seeing your video, only the cowboy.
Okay. Uh, alright, nevermind.
It's okay. Uh, wait, you're looking at the
cowboy, uh, sorry.
The, the blender interface. Okay.
Yeah, I didn't, uh, next time, just, uh,
unmute and let me know.
I, I did not, what are you looking at now?
Okay, you are now looking at the video. Yes, yes, yes.
Okay, well, that in case,
let me play a little bit of it for you.
Uh, let's see, let's do
Here. And histogram
displays effects on top of the simulation.
This course provides practical insights into using the rigid
body system for dynamic and visually impactful scenes.
The particle system can add extra detail
or instance, large numbers of objects like grass, rocks,
or flocks of birds.
When it comes to creating animation,
blender is nearly as good as Maya.
It offers all the essential tools,
including character rigging constraints, a pose editor,
non-linear animation for independent movement forward
and inverse kinematics for fast posing and more.
These features provide animators with the flexibility
and power to create complex animations. Several.
Okay, so, um, that, that's enough of a taste.
Please watch this video later,
and you'll be astounded at that.
This free software is available for you to
wreak havoc on the world with, um,
everything you saw on yesterday's, uh, session that,
that Anastasia gave,
where they had the virtual model walking around
and her clothes are flapping in the wind
and moving with her body.
Uh, that can be done in Blender, uh,
using the physics system that is available for Ben Blender,
the cloth physics system.
Uh, so, but, you know, like, I don't want to get ahead of,
um, where what we need to do today,
but Blender for fashion, uh,
after the Fabric Academy program, I really got into Blender
and I made some of these images, uh,
using the Blender software.
So here I'm using blenders, uh, very cool geometry nodes
to create, uh, uh, a random
grid mesh on top of a make human figure.
And here are some of the results.
Okay? So starting from what I'm going to show you today, uh,
we're going to be able to do some very, very cool things
to prepare for Blender.
Uh, I've already asked you to please have a, uh, computer
that is reasonably powerful, ideally with A GPU installed.
If you don't have this and you try to render
or animate in blender, uh,
it could literally destroy your computer.
Uh, your, your CPU will overheat to a point
where it may never be recoverable.
So please, um, well, like, what,
what's the word they always say?
Like, don't try this at home
unless you have the right equipment.
Uh, so please GPU, uh, if, if you, that, that's something
that you definitely want to have.
And if not, you know, anybody with a Mac
and a Mac, silicon, uh, M two M1
or whatever, you should be good to go.
Uh, otherwise, if you don't have A-G-G-P-U,
it might be difficult three to button mouse.
If you don't have one, get one.
It will, uh, a lot of what I'm going to teach you today,
particularly the shortcuts, involves using the mouse button.
And if you don't have that, uh,
you can do it using a track pad,
but it's like two fingers, three fingers,
it's a lot less, uh, precise.
And make sure you, if you're going to be using this
for this Fabric Academy course,
that you have the latest version installed, which is 4.5 0.3
LTS, and here's a link to download that
software if you haven't already done so.
And for all of our Mac friends here out there in Fabric
Academy lan, I am on a Windows pc.
So a lot of the comments I'll be talking about later will
be, uh, windows commands.
So if I say control, you need to go, uh, use your
squiggly command key.
If I say alt, you need to go use your option key. All right.
Uh, for you Mac folks out there, go ahead
and write that down on a piece of paper
and put it to the side, uh, right now.
So no mouse is possible.
And if you are using only a track pad, you're gonna have
to learn these things.
So two fingers and swiping will get, allow you
to orbit in the scene.
Uh, shift plus two fingers swiping will allow you to pan,
and two fingers pinch will obviously allow you to zoom.
Okay? Okay.
I'm gonna check the chat just
to see if I missed anything important.
Be sure to share all the windows. Okay.
Yeah, we're good so far. All right.
Uh, so the objective today is, so I, I modeled this, uh,
very quickly the other day, uh, all in blender
and hopefully we're gonna tackle this middle one today.
We're gonna see if we can't make a torso, uh, for you today.
Uh, let me get out of here.
Uh, first we're going to learn how
to use the laser slicer add-on for blender.
It does exist, it's not quite as robust
or featureful as the fusion version.
The fusion version allows,
it will automatically number each piece.
It will create like connector slots.
It will put, uh, holes for rods to, to build your models.
None of those features exist.
So what, what a blender can do is take your solid model,
slice it up into whatever number of slices you want,
and those outlines of those slices can be exported
as an SVG image, which can then be, then if you want,
bring it into a software like Illustrator
or Inkscape to add numbers as to like, you know,
which piece goes on top of what other piece.
So, but I mean, it's slices.
Uh, then after that we're gonna set up blend for slicing,
try to understand the interface a little bit, learn
to use some of the modeling tools, learn to use a couple
of modifiers, learn to, uh, how to add materials
to the model to give it, uh, color
and then maybe even get to render.
So, um, we're gonna start at the top
and see how far we get within the next hour and 15 minutes.
We may not get to everything, uh,
but if any of you become super excited by this
and want to learn more, you can ping me on Mattermost,
and I'll be happy to, uh, talk to you one-on-one.
Alright, let's get to the blender, uh, slicing, uh,
for, uh, uh, for Blender.
Yeah. Okay, so let me unshare this screen.
Am I unshared? I can't tell. I am, yes. Okay.
And move my zoom screen out of the way.
And I'm gonna share screen one more time.
Uh, this time we'll share this screen.
Okay. So earlier I accidentally showed you this screen,
which is the, um, screen that I use to do my,
um, cowboy.
Uh, so as you can see, this is
what he looks like when it's in model form.
Uh, this is what the wire frame of this guy looks like.
So I modeled everything from the bullets to the gun,
his holster, his body, his shirt.
In fact, I can turn off all this stuff so you can see, uh,
what cowboy looks like without bullets, without pistol,
without holster, without badge, without a cactus,
without hat, without pants, without shirt.
And so you've got the raw figure that I created here.
Looks a little bit like plastic man,
but it was enough to do the job.
Okay? So let me put that stuff back on.
And then of course, um,
rendering this out will produce something
that looks
like that.
Okay? All right. Um, but we're not gonna go there right now.
I'm going to go ahead and create a new file.
So you go to file New General,
and I'm not gonna save this, and we'll go to here.
So for those of you who want to follow along, um, please get
to this point and
let me know how do, how do we,
how can you let me know when you're ready to go?
Uh, let me see.
Gimme a thumbs up on your, um, screen
so I know you're ready to move on.
Okay, four plugs. Ready. Maybe also get my notes up here.
Okay, cool. All right, so let's, uh, move along here.
Sorry, let me put my zoom window in place
so I can see your faces.
Okay. Um, we're talking about blender model slicing first.
So, uh, first I'm just going to quickly turn this, uh,
generic blender cube into something other than a cube.
Um, you'll notice on the left hand side here
that I have my mouse and my keyboard, uh, key presses.
So you'll see in the recording exactly what I hit in order
to get anything done here.
So I'm going to hit right now the, I'm in edit mode.
I got here by hitting the tab key.
So from object to edit mode, I'm gonna hit the three key.
To do face select mode, I'm gonna select this upper face,
hit E to extrude it s to scale it
e to extrude it again, s to scale it again, b, b
to extrude it again as to scale it out again.
So, okay, I made some kind of very ugly sculpture,
which I will then use to slice.
Okay. And, uh, hit the tab key
to get back out into object mode.
I'll explain all of this later,
and we're just going quickly to get through this.
So, um, blender comes generically with lots
and lots of features, but you can add features to it.
And you do that by going to the edit menu preferences.
And then there's a, a section here called add-ons. Okay?
One of the add-ons that you're gonna want to use for, uh,
uh, for these laser slicing is called laser slicer.
Okay? So if I do my search here, you'll see
that I have already installed it, laser slicer.
Okay? Um, if it doesn't appear in add-ons,
you might have to go to extensions.
And in extensions, you're probably gonna get a button here
that says, is it okay for blender
to connect to the internet?
You definitely want that to be a yes.
And then, um, uh, you're gonna search for
laser slicer, add-on if it doesn't exist, uh,
let me bring this back over here.
If it doesn't exist, you still can't find it.
I'm sorry, I'm getting stuck somewhere here.
Uh, blender's crashing.
Okay, are you seeing my notion notes right now?
I hope
Yes.
Yes. Okay, you can go here, you can go here
to download the, uh, file necessary,
and it's gonna come into your download folder as a zip file.
You do not want to unzip it, okay?
So, uh, you can install it from the zip file by going to
blender again, edit preferences, add-ons,
and then in the upper right hand corner here,
there's a down carrot here,
and then it says install from disc.
So if you click on that
and you look for your, uh, your
laser slicer slash master zip,
and then you click install from disc, it will install it
as an add-on for your blender, uh, installation.
Okay? Uh,
um, great.
Once you have it installed, uh, it, you will access it
by using this side panel here.
There's a small carrot here that faces outward,
so you can pull it out to see, uh, it hidden,
or you can use the N key N like Nancy to pop it out.
So n is to pop it out and in. And there are several tabs.
All of these tabs are add-ons that I've,
I've added into blender.
One of them should say laser. Okay?
So with the laser add-on, uh, up there,
you select your object, you decide
how thick do you want your slices to be?
Right? Now, if I were to slice it,
because, uh, sorry, I'm gonna go to items.
And I see that my object is two meters in the X direction,
two meters in the Y direction,
and nearly six meters in the Z direction.
So it's a proper, like full size sculpture here.
Uh, let me shrink that.
I'm gonna shrink that, I'm going
to scale the whole thing down by five times.
Oops, the other way. Scale minus five.
Nope. Okay, that did not work. Scale.
I'm, I'm just gonna make it really tiny.
Alright, now it's down to about, uh,
a little bit over half a meter tall.
I use the s key to do that.
Okay, once again, back to the laser tab.
Um, now it's looking at 348 slices.
If I use a two millimeter slice, most
of you will be using cardboard to produce this project.
I believe your cardboard in your lab should be about
five millimeters thick.
So I'm gonna do five in here.
And you see that the number of slices gets knocked down
to 139.
Okay? Uh, the next two, uh, width
and height determines sort
of the cutting plane for your object.
So if, you know, going back
to the item tab at the top there,
that your x in the X direction, you're about 0.2 meters.
And in the Y direction you're about 0.2 meters.
So that's, uh, 23 centimeters and 23 centimeters.
You wanna make sure that your cutting, uh,
plane is bigger than that.
So right now I have 450 millimeters, so
that's 45 centimeters, right?
So that's more than adequate to cut.
Uh, so you wanna adjust this one, you wanna adjust this one
and this one, you probably wanna leave the rest of it alone.
Now, the only thing next you need to do is, uh,
decide which folder you want your slices to go into.
I'm going to put, make a folder in my downloads folder
called, uh, test slices.
Okay? And accept, oops,
accept, accept.
Alright, so once you've done that, a button called slice,
the object appears.
So you go ahead and click on slice the Object,
and you can see that if I zoom in
that this object now has these horizontal,
uh, slices throughout.
So over here on, uh, the, in the outliner panel of, uh,
blender, where you have a list of all of the objects
that's in your 3D modeling scene, we have the cube,
which is this sculpture that I made, and I will go ahead
and rename that as sculpture.
And then you have something called slices.
So if I turn off using the eyeball icon,
if I turn off the sculpture, I can,
I can see only the slices.
And here are my, how many number of slices was that?
300 slices. Okay.
So it's already been exported as SVG, uh, to a file.
So I'm going to go ahead
and minimize my window for a second here.
Open my explorer window. Can you see my explorer window?
Yes, you can. Good. And we're going to go
to my download folder, and I have a folder
here called test slices.
And if I go to test slices, I have an SVG file called Cube,
uh, which was the name of the object before I changed it.
Um, let me go ahead
and open that up in Inscape
so you can see what it looks like.
Uh, while it's loading, any questions so far?
Is everybody lost? Are we doing okay?
Thumbs up if you're doing okay.
Scary face if you're not,
all right, I get a Martinez giving me a thumbs up.
Thank you very much. Makes my heart glow. You made my day.
Love you back. Uh, oh.
Textile Academy is giving me an evil skull. That's not good.
Solana is totally lost. Okay? Don't worry about it.
Hopefully we'll get a little bit better.
All right, I'm in, uh, gonna open Inscape here,
and I'm gonna go ahead and drag
and drop that cube file into Inscape and hit okay.
And let me mi maximize that.
And, okay, so all of these squares
are the slices that have been made.
You, you see that they get progressively smaller.
I, I don't know if you can see them. They're very
small, okay?
And unlike, uh, fu uh, fusion Slicer,
it doesn't give you numbers for these,
but, uh, I can see based on experience that the very top
of this is the bottom of the object, right?
Because you can remember my object was fat got smaller,
went up straight, and it got bigger again, right?
So this is fat,
and then it gets, it should at some point.
Ooh, I keep on zooming. I'm sorry about that.
At some point it should get smaller so
that we're still at the bottom of the block,
and now it's starting to get smaller and smaller
and smaller as my object got smaller,
and this is the neck of my sculpture.
And then at the very end, it gets slightly bigger again.
So from bottom to top, left to right would be
how I would create my numbering system.
And this thing is ginormous.
Remember, my thing was, uh, still half a meter in size
and none of you have, um, of cardboard that big.
So you would have to scale this down in order for it
to fit into a laser cutter.
And I believe these are individual objects,
or they're not on individual objects,
but you can break them up by going to, uh, yeah.
Can't remember by, I know you can break up these things into
individual objects, which then you can rearrange
however you need on the page.
Okay? Okay. I've got some questions in the chat, I think.
Okay. Patricia's totally lost.
Uh, Alison's enjoying the ride. Thank you for that.
Um, gave up on working along, but enjoying the ride.
Rico Inscape, did you open
what you are exporting from Blender
or previous SVG from Make Human?
No. Uh, I, yeah, so the, to answer Claire's questions,
the only one I can actually answer, um,
blender created in my download folder,
a folder called Test Slices.
I don't know if you can see it here.
Okay, when I click open Test license, I have one SVG file
inside and I simply dragged
and dropped that SVG file into Inscape
and it opened up the file.
Good, Claire Claire's happy.
All right, with regards to everything else from now on,
I'm going to be talking exclusively Blender.
Uh, but let me just say if I can bring,
find my notes again.
Alright, so I, I kind of walked you
through it here in my notion notes, right?
First I told you how to download the zip file, how
to install, uh, laser Slicer as an add-on for,
um, uh, as an add-on for Blender, uh,
import the Make Human.
So if you happen to have made a make Human body, import it,
but do it as an FBX file.
And you do that here.
Um, if you go to, to file import,
and one of the options here is FBX here, okay?
So if you happen to have made an, uh, a make human figure,
you will import it here and it'll come in,
and then you'll apply, you select it,
and then apply all of the things I did here.
So the first thing you're going to want to do, probably
for your make human figures, to scale it to something
that you know will actually fit in a laser, uh, uh, cutter.
So if you go into Blender
and your figure is two meters tall,
it's gonna generate slices that are way too big
for your laser cutter to deal with.
And I'll show you how to scale
or know how big everything is when I go into Blender proper.
Any other questions on slicer before I move on?
The whole point here is that, uh, slicer is available
as a feature inside a blender.
You simply have to just add it on first.
Lemme go back to my notes. All right?
So here I say, yeah,
Uh, I, uh, could you understand the slice, uh,
how you slice the object?
Um, that part was understandable for me.
Understandable. You cannot understand. Yeah.
Oh, you cannot. Okay.
Um, you know what, I'll do it one more time.
Uh, I'm gonna make a new object. Yeah, no problem.
So let, let's make a curvy figure since, uh,
I'm gonna delete my sculpture here since it's ugly.
Anyway, um, delete. All right, no more sculpture.
Uh, these are my slices.
I'm gonna delete these slices now as well, so
that they don't confuse you.
Take my sculpture and delete that.
I just hit the delete here. Oh, yeah, you can see that
shift a to add something, and I'm going to add a UV sphere.
I'm gonna add a circle. Alright. All right.
So once again, if you hit the end key,
the side panel pops in
and out here on the right hand side, you'll want to go
to the item tab.
The item tab will tell you all of the information you need
to know about your object.
So if you look at dimensions here, you see that in the x,
which is indicated by the red line Y, which is indicated
by the green line and Z direction, which is indicated
by the blue line up here, uh, that the ball is two meters
by two meters by two meters.
Are we good about that?
Everybody's seeing the dimension here.
So two meters is two big, right?
So a, a, a typical laser cutter has a cutting bed
of probably 500 millimeters or something like that.
So let, let's shrink this guy down.
So to scale an object down, I use s for scale,
and then just make this smaller.
I'm, and I'm watching my dimensions, right?
Right now it's one meter,
and now it's okay,
4, 4 47 centimeters.
Right now
I am missing this, uh, side, um, toolbar.
Hit the end key with your cursor
on the, uh, modeling window.
If you hit the end key, it will toggle it in and out.
And you wanna be in the item tab to be able
to see the dimensions of, of your object.
And if you want it to be a specific dimension, uh,
this is the magic here.
I can click and drag, make all of those things dark,
and I'm gonna put it at 0.4 to make it spec exactly
40 centimeters in dimension.
All right, and just to show you, uh, you,
you see up at the top location,
you see that it has rotation.
So if I take this cube
and I move it, you'll see that my x, y,
and Z values, uh, change.
Okay? So now I'm only moving into the X direction
and you see that the values change.
Um, so I'm gonna leave it in the middle for now,
but this item, uh, tab is super useful for understanding
where your geometry is existing in blender space.
Okay? Uh, who, who asked that question earlier?
I think, uh, s Lana, I think.
But, uh, I'm gonna show you how to slice now.
Okay, so now for, I'm gonna move from the items tab down
to the laser tab.
Okay? The object is selected.
I know it's selected because it has a yellow outline.
If I click outside of the ball,
the yellow outline disappears.
If I click on the object, a yellow outline appears,
and now it's ready to be sliced In the slicer menu,
you see at the very bottom there, it, it says number
of slices for me, it says 80 slices.
All right? Assuming that I use a five millimeter thickness
as the slicing separation, uh, it,
it's 80, that, that's a lot.
So I'm gonna change that to 10 millimeters,
and now I get 40 slices.
Who was it that asked the question?
Lili, Lili, Lili, are you, are you following me so far?
Uh, I try to follow, now I want
to find the slicer tool.
Ah, Okay, you haven't even installed it
yet. Okay, no worries.
You'll Lilith joined a little bit later
and she missed the downloading of the add-on.
Okay? Yeah. For, for now, just watch me slice this thing
and then you can, uh, install the software,
the, uh, add-on later.
So you, the three things you want to, uh, you want
to make sure to adjust is, uh, the thickness of the slice,
because that will determine how many slices you generate.
The next thing is the, the, the knife,
the slicing plane that you are going to use.
You know that this object here is 4,400
millimeters in diameter.
Right now my cutting plane is 450 width
and 450 heights.
So that should work in the X and Y direction.
It's slightly bigger than my object, so that, that's going
to work very, very nicely.
Do not touch DBI.
If you want, you can change the line color
to something else, whatever pretty color you want,
but you know, it doesn't really matter so much.
Do not touch thickness.
Uh, probably do not touch cut spacing.
And, uh, SVG polygons
controls the speed and accuracy of the slicing.
I've never used this before.
Uh, I'm not, I'm gonna leave it unchecked for now,
but you guys can experiment with using it and not using it.
And then the last one here is the file folder where you want
to be dropping, uh, this into, okay?
Alright. So no, remember that my object is called sphere.
When I, when I, uh, slice this object, you're going
to see a bunch of slices called sphere.
All right? So with that, I hit slice object and it's done.
And what you see here in the outliner, uh,
menu over here is a new item called slices.
So if I turn off the visibility of my sphere
by clicking on the eyeball icon,
you'll see just the slices, okay?
And once again, if we go back out to my Windows Explorer
into my downloads folder,
because that's where I told it to go,
and I go to my test license, um, folder, you'll see a new
SVG here called Sphere.
And I can go ahead and bring that into Inkscape.
Okay? I'm gonna delete this first one first. Clear that out.
Um, now I'm gonna take my sphere,
click, drag, hit, okay, and I've got my circles.
Okay. And you can see that it goes from top to bottom.
So here are the tiny circles, and it gets bigger and bigger
and bigger, and then it gets smaller again.
So in Inscape, uh,
or Illustrator, hopefully you know how to use it already,
but if you wanna number these things, you can just go
to the text tool, go in here
and type the number one here, type the number two,
type number three, and so on so forth, so that when you, uh,
laser cut it, you can have an indication
of which pieces go where.
Okay? It takes a little bit more time than the fusion
slicer, but you can, uh, do it for free, uh, without, uh,
having the headache of the Fusion Slicer software.
Was that adequate? Lili?
Okay, I think I'm totally going over time. Yes, thank you.
Yeah, no problem. Okay, so let me, uh, move on.
All right, so that's, that's it for, yeah.
So these are the steps on, uh, what you need
to do using this Slicer software.
Hopefully this is helpful
and you can even visualize the slices too.
You can do all, all of these other things,
which is not necessary
to do the assignment work for this week.
Okay? So let's get into Blender proper here.
Um, I've been throwing out a lot of terms for you,
and Sal told me that one
of the biggest headaches when it comes to blenders,
understanding this crazy interface.
So I'm going to try to make it easy for you
and say that there's only a few things you need to see
or pay attention to when it comes
to knowing the blender interface enough for you
to model a torso for this week.
Okay? Uh,
we've been playing in something called a 3D view port.
Okay? So that's where the modeling the magic happens
in the 3D view port.
A couple of locations that you need to pay attention to.
Upper right hand corner are view modes.
So when I showed off my cowboy, I took it from wire frame
to solid to rendered view.
That happens by clicking on these little, uh, circles.
And each, you know, you have like a circle with lines in it.
That's wire frame. The next one is called solid.
The next one is material preview,
and the last one is rendered.
Okay? The other one you wanna pay attention
to on the left side here is a window
that currently says object mode.
And previously when I was messing around, I hit the tab key
and I toggled back and forth between object and edit mode.
I'll explain what those two modes are later,
but that's where you want to be paying attention to see
what mode of operation you currently are.
Great. That's the 3D view port so far.
On the upper right hand corner is
something called the outliner.
So for Windows user, this would be equivalent to your
file explorer, okay?
Everything that is in your 3D view port, every object, uh,
will be listed here as an item in your outliner.
So if you look at this particular example, you see
that there are three items, an area light,
a camera, and a cube.
Let me show you in real world example what this looks like.
In my scene right now.
If you look at my outliner, you probably cannot read it.
Um, I have four things.
I have an area light, so if I click on it,
it highlights in the window.
There's my area light.
I have a camera, I have a sphere,
and I have the slices.
Okay? So this, this is where you, uh,
list all of your things.
And I have two folders in here, okay?
I have a folder called collections and a
and a folder called assets.
Uh, the first keyboard shortcut I'm going
to teach you is CC like cat
with your cursor hovering over the outliner window.
Uh, if you click on scene collection,
which is the very top folder,
and you type the letter C, you'll get a new folder.
So I have one here now called collection three.
And I would highly, you know, for recommend that you rename
that to something that you can understand, like, um, torso.
I don't know. I'll just call it that for now. All right.
So if you need to make extra folders, it's c
for collection in the outliner window keyboard.
Shortcuts in, in blender changes depending on
where your cursor is.
So c if it's hovering over the, uh,
3D view port will generate a completely different result
than it does if it's hovering over the outliner.
The outliner, as far as I know,
only has one keyboard shortcut, and that is C for collection
or creating a new folder.
Right? Back to my notes.
Uh, the next very important window for you to pay attention
to is the properties window in the lower right hand
corner, okay?
The properties windows has lots and lots of icons, lots
and lots of features for which
you can control their properties,
but the ones that you probably want to pay attention
to the most, and Nuria had asked me to put this in my notes
and I forgot to do it,
but, so hopefully you will, uh, hear me and pay attention.
Near the very top, you'll see an icon
that looks like the back of A-D-S-L-R camera, okay?
This is the render, uh, setting.
So this will be very important later on when we give, uh,
want to show off our object with colors and lights
and so on so forth.
The next, uh, uh, icon down looks like a printer, right?
A machine that's spitting out a piece of paper.
This is for output.
Uh, so when we want to output an image
or we want to output a video, this is where we're going
to set, uh, settings for like, do we want it to be a PNG
or a JP a JPEG image
or with video, do we want it to be MP four
or some other format?
So all of your settings
for output will be in the second icon.
Okay? We're gonna skip a few.
Uh, there's a fourth,
the fourth one down looks like a water droplet.
That one is your scene properties window.
And this one is, uh, important for one thing,
which is the units menu.
This is where you want to go
and make sure that you're in metric,
or if you wanna do, uh, imperial, you know,
use inches, that that's fine.
But this is where you wanna set your,
uh, measurement system.
And uh, here it's, the length is currently in meters.
I'm gonna leave it in here for now.
I'm not gonna change anything.
My blender defaults to metric unit, system
and meters length.
I'm not sure what yours is,
but if you need to change it, this is where you do it.
Alright? So that's render output and scene.
The next one you wanna pay attention to, uh,
will appear when you click on an object.
So I'm going to delete slices
'cause I don't need that right now.
I'm going to click on the sphere that I created,
and then you see this blue wrench icon show up, okay?
The blue wrench icon, when, when I select an object,
the blue wrench icon is for modifiers.
Later on in, in this tutorial, I'll show you how
to use modifiers to do very interesting things with this.
So yesterday, I think, you know, you know what,
I'm gonna skip ahead and show you some fancy stuff.
Now, yesterday you saw some beautiful human beings, right?
That were create turned into wire frame skeletons.
Well, let me show you how quickly
and easily you can do that in blender.
So we're gonna go to add modifier, generate, um,
wire frame, boom, done
one modifier, and you,
you've just changed a shape into a wire frame model.
Later on, when I bring in a human,
I'm gonna do the same thing to it,
and you can see how easily, uh, that can be done.
This is why Blender is so powerful,
because it, it can do fancy stuff like that.
Super, super quick.
Um, if you don't like this for any reason, uh,
blender is non-destructive.
Like, so this wire frame modifier is a,
you are looking at it in preview mo mode until you apply it.
And the way you apply it is by,
there's a down carrot up here.
If you click on that, you see the word apply.
If you apply it, it will be permanent.
If for whatever reason you're like, nah, I don't like that,
you can hit the x mark next to it
and it removes that modifier, wire frame's gone.
Okay? So just to reminder
that the modifier is not permanent
until you apply it.
Okay? Uh, where are we in the notes?
Uh, alright.
And then you have a bottom window here,
which I call the auxiliary window, which means
that it can be anything that you want.
So this 3D viewport window happens to be that way
because blender chose to assign 3D port to this giant window
blender chose to assign outliner
to the upper right hand corner, chose to assign, uh,
properties to the lower right hand corner,
but in fact, these windows can be
anything that you want it to be.
So if you go to the upper left hand corner of the window
and click on the icon, you can choose one of the many,
many options for this window to become.
So if for whatever reason you want a second 3D viewport
window, you can do that and you can choose this.
And now I have a second 3D viewport window.
So when I make an adjustment to this object,
you'll see it happening in both windows.
All right? Uh, if you want, for whatever reason,
you want another properties window in here,
you can go over here, click properties,
and now you have two properties, windows,
which is probably not necessary.
Probably, uh, when you open your blender, uh,
it should be on something called timeline, which is used
for animation, right?
The number one to 250 here, uh, represents frames 101
to 150.
So if I move this icon and,
and lock in its position over the
frames, I can show some animation.
We're not gonna get to animation today.
For now, I'm actually not going
to use the bottom window at all.
And just use these three windows.
Uh, 3D, viewport, outliner and properties.
Um, uh, Anastasia, Claudia, please let me know
how badly over time I am.
Uh, and then tell me to move along, uh, if, if necessary.
Okay. So the, uh, blender is a Cartesian.
You have one more hour.
Okay, great, great, great. How are we doing so far?
Is everybody still like completely confused?
And everybody Okay?
A big part. Anxious to get this human inside the blender.
Oh yeah, we'll get there. We'll get there.
I know this is painful that I'm going
through like a grade school teacher,
but you'll thank me for this later, I promise you.
Okay. So it's our Cartesian, uh, coordinate system,
modeling system, meaning that we're going
to be operating using X, Y,
and Z to reference where this object is in blender space.
Okay? Uh, the green line, as I indicated
before, is represents the X direct, uh, sorry,
the Y direction.
The red line indicates the, uh, X direction
and the blue line represents the, uh, zed direction.
And the convention in blender is minus Y,
which is currently this side of the ball is the front
of the object plus y as I'm pointing to this, uh, sort
of gumball object on the upper right hand corner.
Right now, a positive Y is the back of the object minus y,
which is over in this territory, is the right side
of the object positive.
Uh, sorry, I said Y minus X is the right side of the object.
Positive X is the left side of the object
positive Zed is the top of the object.
And, uh, minus zed is the bottom of the object.
So please use this convention.
It will help you to organize your life,
uh, a little bit, uh, easier.
And now I'm going to get to this little gumball.
Oh, I haven't done navigation yet.
Uh, I believe that's where we are right now, right?
Let me see, uh, my notes collections.
We did eyeball camera. Okay, I did not talk about that.
So talk about Cartesian. Boy, I'm all over the place.
All right, let me see if I can get through renderings,
settings, camera, printer icon.
Okay, so we've walked through, uh, the properties window.
So the camera icon, printer icon, droplet icon, blue wrench.
Oh, I didn't get to red checker ball.
Um, so with the object selected, the last, uh,
modifier, or sorry, the last property icon
that you should pay attention
to is this red ball with a checker on it.
And this is materials.
This is where we will assign colors to our object.
Okay, we'll do that a little bit later.
So once again, camera icon, printer icon,
water droplet icon, blue wrench, icon,
and the red ball icon.
Those are the only things you need to pay attention to.
The other ones are fancy
and we'll get to that in later sessions.
Um, I talked, talked to you about C over here.
Uh, what else in my notes am I forgetting?
Okay, auxiliary, we talked about that already. Outliner.
Okay, let me, I didn't talk about enough about the outline.
So for every object here, I'm gonna click on sphere.
The moment I do that, it gets a yellow outline to the right
of sphere, there are two icons, a eyeball,
eyeball looking icon, and a camera icon.
If I click the eyeball icon, the, uh, ball disappears.
It gets hidden. Okay?
So when you want an object to be hidden from view,
you click on the eyeball.
Clicking on it again, will make it come back into life.
The camera icon, on the other hand, is used
for keeping it from being rendered
or allowing it to be rendered.
So if the camera icon is, is visible, then it means
that this object will be rendered when you render.
Uh, so if you know later on, if you have five
or six objects in your scene
and you want certain objects
to be hidden away from rendering,
you will click on the camera icon
to keep it from being rendered.
Okay? All right.
That's the outliner, uh, view modes.
Okay, let me talk about view modes
and then these two things.
Okay? I mentioned earlier
that in the upper right hand corner
of the screen over here have your various, um,
view modes for your object.
Currently, uh, I'm in solid mode, which is being, uh,
sort of highlighted in blue.
If I move to the left of that
and I click the other one, I get a wire frame mode.
If I go to the third one, the one on the right
of the solid view, I get what is called a material preview.
And you can kind of see that what happens here is you,
you get a little bit of shading happening on the object,
depending on the intensity of your light.
And then lastly, if you click on your rendered, uh, icon,
it will show this with kind of light effects, um, uh,
applied over your object for the purposes
of modeling an object.
You want to stay away from the last two view modes
because these two view modes are the most demanding
on your computer's, GPU and CPU.
So unless you really have to see it in its full,
beautiful rendered shadowed stuff, uh, avoid being there
because it, it, it will make your computer heat up
and, uh, completely or, or,
or potentially destroy it if it's, uh, not powerful enough.
So stick to this second one shaded mode
or wire frame mode while you're making
adjustments to your object.
Okay? And then I said on the upper left hand corner,
object mode and edit mode, I want you to think
of object mode as being big changes to your,
all of your object.
So for instance, if I want to move it
and to move something, I need to click the G key instead
of m uh, G for grab.
And then I can follow that up with either an X, Y,
or a Z to constrain it to a, uh, an axis.
For instance, I'm gonna move it on the red line,
so I'm gonna hit the X key next,
and now I can just move this ball left and right.
Okay, so I'm moving the entire ball, all right?
Or if I want to scale this, I hit the S key,
I can scale the whole ball.
And you're asking me, what, what do you mean whole ball?
What else is there? So if I hit the tab key,
I'm going to go to edit mode.
Now on the upper left hand corner,
it has now changed from edit to, uh, I'm sorry,
from object to edit mode.
And now I can make micro changes to my object as soon
as I get into edit mode.
I have three selection options for, uh, my object.
I'm getting a little bit ahead of time here.
First of all, earlier, uh,
Anastasia talked about mesh modeling.
Do you guys know what that means?
Who knows what mesh modeling means?
Um, I know, Okay, go ahead.
Uh, it's like, uh, small pieces.
What make our course, um, have the,
uh, have the type
and, uh, like we, uh, if we, they do some faces,
it's like we have, uh, our eyes
and, uh, it have some, uh, seer types
and, uh, it's like small pieces.
What can, uh, make curves, uh,
and mm, broke okay, some little parts,
the objects mm-hmm.
To manipulate it, to change it, uh,
and, uh, could, uh, do anything what you want
with it. Love.
Perfect, perfect. That was,
that was exactly what I needed to hear.
So we have a ball, right?
But if you wanna do something other in ball, I,
I want you to imagine this.
Somebody was asking earlier about adding arms,
an extra arm in blender, uh, or,
or to, to their make human object.
So if, if this were a human, I would select the arm,
copy it, drag it around,
and shove it somewhere else so it has an extra arm, okay?
Uh, and you can do that
because the geometry in this case, it's a sphere,
is being subdivided into smaller faces.
Okay? So these selection modes, the third one,
or if I hit the number three on my keyboard, I can go ahead
and select a, uh, sorry,
lemme just change my selection mode here.
Okay? If I,
now I can select a face on this object,
And the kind of things I was doing earlier,
and I'm, I'm getting ahead of myself
'cause I was gonna teach you the keyboard shortcuts later.
But let, let's learn one right now, G is to move something.
Okay? So grab, we're gonna grab a face and move it.
So I'm grabbing this face, and just like
before, I'm going to do G
and then X to move it along the red line.
So go to GX.
Now I can like pull this face out, right?
So if this were a, a solid sphere
and it had no subdivisions, you wouldn't be able
to manipulate it in this way, right?
So that's, if I want to select a face and manipulate it.
The second, uh, option to manipulate this object is
to select one of the edges, one of these lines
that makes up the faces.
So type two on the keyboard, click as an edge,
and I'm gonna do G and this time Z to move it up and down.
Okay? So there, so I've got two spikes on this ball.
And then the last selection mode that we can go
for is vertex.
So that's number one on the keyboard.
And that's to get these little dots
that are the intersections of all the lines.
And once again, let's do g
and this time y to pull it on the Y direction.
So these subdivisions, the of the geometry, uh, allows you
vertex edge
and face control points that you can utilize to, uh,
manipulate a geometry.
In this case, it was a sphere, right?
So when I'm done with that, so I, I said in edit mode,
you can go inside and micro adjust the object.
So let's say, I'll take this point here now,
and I'm going to hit the same earlier I scaled the ball,
I'm going to hit the S key
and I'm gonna scale, oh, scale doesn't work on this one,
but no scale will not work.
Uh, what can I scale? I can scale a face. All right?
So let me go and select go to three to do face select,
click on this object, hit S to scale.
And I can scale out this face
right a little bit ahead of ourselves.
I just hit tab to get back to object mode.
Now I can no longer access those, uh, edge face
or vertex points to delete this thing.
I can only grab the whole thing and move it around.
So that's the difference between object
and uh, edit mode, right?
Um,
great.
Um, I'm gonna close this up.
That's the
interface settings.
Alright, later on, not right now, uh, these are the add-ons
that I use, uh, in my
normal blender life laser cut slicer,
I already mentioned that to you.
You're going to use one called bull tool.
And this is to answer Anastasia's question
about using bullions.
Uh, loop tools are super, super helpful
that you're gonna do add-on.
Once again, edit preferences, add on, look
for these specific names.
Uh, there's a make human plugin so that you no longer have
to make the model outside of blender imported in.
You can make the model inside a blender right away,
and I'll show you that in a second.
And then these other ones for the future, when we get
to do the second session and,
and fancier things, uh, in this section I show you how
to adjust your units, right?
Remember it's the water droplet icon. I'll go ahead, okay?
And then if you want to change metric, you go
to scene units, unit system metric.
If you want to change the unit scale,
you would do it there and so on and so forth.
Outliner, I already explained to you.
Um, so these names here,
environmental folder and assets folder.
This is what I usually call my collections.
So right now my, this top collection with the light
and the camera is called collection.
And I normally and change that to environment.
And inside this folder,
I always have just the light and the camera.
My sphere, which is the object I usually drag
and stick into assets.
Okay? I'm gonna delete the torso
folder so it doesn't confuse you.
So I have us, I start off usually
with two subfolders environment and assets.
And in assets is this craziest sculpture that I made.
Great. Alright, so that's settings.
Uh, like I said, you have access to my notion page.
You can go ahead and look at these things
at ad nauseum later.
Uh, I already talked about the cor core Cartesian coordinate
space that you'll be working with.
Now let's learn how to navigate, uh, on your, um,
on your blender screen using a three button mouse.
MMB, by the way, stands for middle mouse button.
Uh, MMB scroll means you use,
you scroll your middle mouse button up
or down, uh, okay, so that, that's what that means.
And shift plus MMB means you have
to hold down the shift key while you're using
the middle mouse button.
So in blender, if I hold down my middle mouse button
and drag it around, I can orbit around the object.
I can look at the back side, front, top,
however I wanna look.
So give that a go.
Another way to do that is
to use this colorful gumball thing at the top here.
If you hold your cursor over that,
it should turn gray, a gray circle.
If you left mouse, click there.
You can also do an orbit around your object
by using that icon.
And this, this gumball is particularly useful
because if you want to snap to a front view, remember
what I said, minus Y is the front view, I click on minus y,
it will automatically snap to that view.
If I wanna look at this object directly from the top,
I can click on the positive Z button
and it will pop you to, uh, the top of the object.
Similarly, uh,
positive X will show me the right side of the object.
So sometimes this is useful.
Once you get it like that, then you can once again go back
to orbiting using your middle mouse button.
If you hold the shift key
and use your middle mouse button,
you can pan your object right, left up, down
without rotating it.
Okay? So shift and middle mouse button, we'll do this.
And then your middle scroll wheel will allow you
to zoom in and out of your object.
So please get used to doing that with your,
with your mouse.
Great. We're almost at the good time.
Do we need a bio break? Everybody?
Okay. Can we go for another 10 minutes
and then we'll do a bio break.
Good. Giselle's, gimme a thumbs up. Thank you, Giselle.
All right, blender navigation.
All right, finally, we're at, uh, modeling.
So as I mentioned, uh, we're going
to be dealing with meshes.
Uh, we're going to be dealing with a surface
that has been subdivided,
and you'll have three ways of manipulating this surface.
Uh, you can select the vertices, which are the intersection
of the lines, one of the edges
or an entire face to manipulate it.
And I demonstrated that.
Uh, so Blender is not a CAD software.
And the, the distinction here is a typical CAD software, uh,
was born from the idea back in the day when architects used
to draw lines on paper and in two dimensions,
and then they used that to extrude up into three dimensions.
As you can see from blender,
the first object it gives you is a three dimensional object.
So it's, it's a 3D, uh, design and animation tool.
It's not a traditional CAD tool.
It doesn't have that kind of, um, I mean, as you saw,
I mean, we can, we can give it specific dimensions,
but dimensionality is not, its priority CAD tools
because it's for architecture
and engineering, you know,
having specific dimensions matters.
But, uh, for blender, uh, making the form comes first
and the dimensions is sort of secondary.
Uh, I already mentioned that it's a mesh.
I already mentioned that we're gonna deal be dealing
with vertex edges and faces to manipulate the shapes
and, uh, generate custom geometric forms by pushing
and pulling on those control points.
These are all, uh, shortcuts to blenders official,
uh, pages.
And you can click on these to get there.
Uh, these, the following shortcuts are windows specific.
So a warning to the Mac people that you're going to have
to remember, control is equal to command,
and alt is equal to options.
All right, the first thing, uh,
I already told you about the C key, uh, yeah,
what I meant here, shortcuts
or windows specific mean that your cursor needs
to be hovering over the 3D viewport
or the outliner in order to get to use the key, uh,
the key keyboard shortcuts.
If it's not here, if it's not, if it's here
and you're typing c,
you're gonna get a very different result than if you were
over here, uh, which will give you a folder, okay?
So please be mindful of where your cursor is placed
as you use these keyboard shortcuts.
The second thing, blender does not auto savee.
So get into the habit of doing Ctrl S
or command S to save your file, uh, periodically.
Otherwise, you're gonna do 30 minutes worth
of beautiful modeling,
and you're gonna lose it all when your computer crashes.
Okay? So please get into the habit
of when you wanna take a stretch.
Control s when you wanna yawn control s I'm boring Jesse.
I can see him, uh, losing it there a little bit.
No worries, no worries. Uh, a a a wonderful feature
that I use a lot is CTRL Alt S
or Command Option S for for Mac people.
This will save the same file,
but do it as a ne uh, ano another version.
So here's an example. Right now my file is unsafe.
You look in the upper left hand corner, it says unsafe.
It has an asterisk there.
So I'm going to go ahead and control S and save this file.
Oops. Control S,
and no, it's not saving y oh,
because I have, I'm in some kind of command, okay?
Control S and I'm going to go ahead
and put it into my downloads folder.
And I'm gonna call this tutorial and safe.
And you notice the name is Tutorial Blend. Okay?
So if I do an incremental save
or file Incremental Safe with the keyboard shortcut Control
Alt S, what ends up happening is,
now my file is called Tutorial one Blend.
So if I wanna keep a previous version
before I make this thing super ugly, somehow, you know,
let's say I go over here and,
and, you know, I'll do a couple more spikes
that are unseemly, um, no, something like that.
I'm like, Ugh, really hate that. You now have two files.
You have a tutorial file and tutorial one file,
or if you want to clip this super ugly version as
yet another version, you can do control alts s
and now we're at tutorial two Blend.
Okay, so, uh, incremental save is something
super useful for you to play with.
Um, I mentioned, uh, wire frame, solid view,
material preview view, render view.
There are actually keyboard shortcuts for that as well.
Um, so if you are in object mode
and you want to get into, uh, wire frame view,
you can do Z four and you'll get into wireframe.
But it's hard to remember, uh, when you hit the Z key,
it gives you this kind of exploded
option of where you wanna go.
And so let's say if wanna go to render,
I can just point the mouse that way.
I go to rendered Z material preview Z solid.
Okay? So that's a quick way for you to get to
a different view, but like I said, for the purposes
of modeling, I would stick to either wire frame or solid.
Do not use the other, uh, options
because it's, uh, going to be tough on your computer.
Alright, so, um, adding geometry to your window,
you're gonna use shift A to add anything.
So if I go back to my blender window,
and I'm gonna do shift a, I will get,
be presented with this menu.
And if I know what I want, for instance, I want a mesh cube,
I can just start typing CUB like that,
and it will kind of filter, select the, the things
with the word CUB in it.
So I see that my top option right now is a mesh cube.
So I'll hit enter and I get a giant cube that eats my
other object there.
Okay? So shift A will add stuff to your,
um, window.
Uh, now we're going to G we've already used G
to move the object.
So with this cube, if I had G
and I can, it can move it around freely, or I can do G
and constrain it to an axis, let's say the y axis this time,
so I can move it back and forth only.
All right? Uh, the next command we're gonna learn is scale.
Scale is, uh, to make it smaller or bigger.
And once again, you can constrain the scaling to one
of the axes if you wish.
So if I, if you want to scale the object down, I,
I recommend that you keep your cursor a little bit further
away from the object because you're going
to be pushing in on the object to make it smaller.
If you wanna make it bigger, you're going to start closer
to the object and be dragging it out.
This time, I want to make it smaller,
so I'll start a little bit further away and type s
and this, uh, line comes
and I just sort of move my mouse towards the object,
and it gets smaller and smaller and smaller,
and it does it in every single axis Right?
Now, what if I only wanna make it shorter, I can go s
and this time Z to con to make it squish
in the Z direction only.
Now I wanna make it longer in the Y direction.
I can go s and then y
and I can make it now longer in the Y direction.
Now I wanna squish it in the Z direction, the red line,
I can go SX
and then I can squish it to make a, a beam or a bar
or something like that, right?
So scale is super useful for that,
is typing the scale parameter, the best way
to scale it to a specific site.
Thank you for that question.
So, um, let's see.
So I'm going to hit the end key to get my side panel
to come up, click on the item tab.
So my, right now, my, my cube is exactly two meters
by two meters by two meters, right?
So to answer Claire's question, if I want this
to become one meter by one meter by one meter, I'm going
to scale it downwards by 0.5, right?
So what you can do is you can click on the object type S
and follow that up with 0.5,
and it will scale it exactly to one by one by one.
So you can be precise with blender if you know exactly,
uh, where you want it to go.
And you could do math in your head. Do you have
to use the multiple of how small to scale?
What is that? I don't understand the question.
Or can you type the specific?
Yes, you can type the specific dimension as well.
So Claire, how, how big do you want my cube to be?
Gimme some dimensions in the x, y, and Z direction.
You can type it or you can talk to me. Okay?
Okay, I'll just talk to you. Sorry, feedback going on.
I think that's better. Um, I, let's say it's, um,
two meters by 5.5 meters by three meters.
Three, okay, so two meters in the X direction.
So I go to the x, uh, panel here and type two
and Y was 5.5, right?
5.5. And then what was the Z direction?
Three. Okay, three. Boom, done.
Okay, wonderful.
All right, so that's scaling.
Uh, the next command that you'll need to know is rotate.
Okay? Uh, generally speaking, you want to be rotating
while looking directly at the object.
And let me explain why. If I rotate it now, it's going,
there's going to be an imaginary axis between the, the my
between my eyes at the screen.
And this is what's going to happen if I hit R to rotate
and I rotate, it rotates on an imaginary axis
between my face and the screen.
If you want to rotate it on just the y axis,
you must follow R with Y
and then it rotates on the y axis only,
and it is still a little bit confusing.
So what you should do is go look at this thing
from the front, right?
So click on the minus y button on the gumball up there.
So you're looking straight on at the object,
and now you type Ry and you can see the rotation.
And just like before, if you want to rotate,
this is specific angle, somebody gimme an angle in the chat,
gimme an angle, any angle.
13, first person gets 38, Lili says 38.
So you type three eight.
And now the, the cube has rotated in the Y direction exactly
38 degrees, okay?
And now it's, it's tilted on its side.
Okay, let's rotate it in the Y direction.
So I'm gonna go to Y and look at it straight on
and go r gimme another angle, just all set.
22.5. Okay, two, 2.5.
It's now rotated in the wide around the Y axis
by exactly 22.5 degrees.
All right? So that's rotation.
Again. Do not use rotation without looking directly at the
object, because it's going to confuse you.
It's going to do weird things that you,
you do not understand.
And I think you already know if I wanna undo anything,
you can just do command or control Z
and it will undo all of the changes you just made.
And while we're on Undo blender is lovely,
especially if you have a powerful computer
with a big hard drive, you can go to edit
Preferences system.
And here in Memory and Limits, it has und undo steps.
Uh, the default I think is 32.
I put 150 just to make sure I have plenty of room
of und undoes to, to do any crazy stupid things that I do.
All right? So I do not recommend this for a,
a older computer because, uh, it will crash your computer.
It, it, uh, defaults at 32.
So somewhere better than 32, I would change that to, uh,
so you can have lots and lots of undue steps.
Okay? All right, next on the menu
we've got, alright, that.
Now this is where we manipulate things.
So before we get here, I'm going to go ahead
and do what Anastasia has been wanting me to do
for this entire time, which is to break in a human.
But before we do that, uh, I'm gonna give you a little bit
of a break, uh, so
that you don't ex your brain doesn't explode.
Uh, so five minutes, yeah, thumbs up.
Okay, so see you in five.
And if anybody wants to stick around
and ask me a question, go ahead.
Yes, I am going, going to keep on moving.
Alright, so, uh, with no further ado, I am going
to bring in a make human, uh, person.
So I'm going to go ahead and hide these two objects
'cause it's just gonna get in the way.
So once again, go to the outliner window,
click on the eyeball icon, and they go to sleep.
Um, you have to, I'm pretty sure
that the make human add-on must be installed using,
uh, the install from disc, uh, option.
I think you have to go and get it
and, uh, install it from the zip file.
Uh, I believe I left instructions in my notes
on how to do that.
Did I not do that? Make human,
uh, blender settings?
Goodness, if I did not do it, I will.
Uh, oh, okay. So I did, I did, I did not share how
to install the add-on into here.
I'll, I'll add that section somewhere in here
and let you know when it's done.
Okay, sorry about that.
Okay, so back to my shortcut list.
So I've installed Make Human into Blender
and it is a, uh, option here on the right side.
It's MPFB, uh, make human plugin
for Blender, MPFP.
So if I click that, uh, I can go to new Human from scratch
and just like what Anastasia showed you later, gender,
we'll leave it as neutral age, young muscle, average weight,
average height, average proportions,
average race, universal.
That's fine with me. Uh, breasts, larger, more firm.
Oh my God, I'm not gonna get into that.
And then lastly, there's a button here called Make
Human or Create Human.
So I click and boom, I get a do
or a Universal person.
Okay? And just to prove to you that we're not dealing
with a solid, but we're dealing with a mesh.
I can go wire frame on this person
and you can see that it is a wire a mesh.
Okay? And if I hit tab
and I'm in, uh, vertex Select, I,
I will have those dot intersections that I can
for I select one, take G and grab it,
and I can create spikes out of my friend here for no reason.
Okay? And then I go back to this mode,
I can go to solid view and now my dude has spikes.
Okay? So, uh, I'm gonna undo all of those, that craziness
and go back here.
All right? So that, that was as easy as
what Anas Ashley showed.
All of the features that you can do in the make human
external software can be done here.
I believe there's like, here Apply assets is
where you can add like skins
and, um, oh, I need to load.
Okay, let's load this skin.
I don't think I've loaded it yet.
Um, but the, all of the clothing
and stuff like that, I think I need
to like install it first,
which I'm pretty sure I haven't done.
Uh, 'cause we're not gonna really do that today.
Uh, but just to show you that yes,
make human is absolutely possible.
And then, um, Anastasia wanted me to show you
how to do a bullion.
Okay? Anybody know what a bullion is?
No. Okay, so a bullion is a mathematical operation
that will take two geometries
and either join them together, use them to cut holes,
use one to cut hole out of another one,
or use them to create like the,
to produce the intersection point only or things like that.
It, it's mathematics to, uh, take two
distinct geometries and use them to influence the other.
Okay? So I mentioned earlier about an add-in called bull
tool and it's awesome.
Okay, so if I go to my edit tab here,
I have bull tool is not activated.
Okay? So I need to go to edit preferences, add-ons,
I'm gonna look for bull tool.
There it is, okay, it is activated.
Why is it not showing up?
Oops, end panel.
Uh, edit. Why is it not here?
Hmm,
sorry guys.
Gimme a second here while I try to debug what's going on
with my blender
preferences Bull tool.
I'll turn it off and on again. There it is.
Okay, so I'll then in my edit menu,
I will have a, uh, thing called bullion.
All right? So let's do fun things with this.
I'm going to add another object shift, A to add,
and I'm going to add in a cube
and I'm gonna scale it down a little bit.
Scale in the X direction, something like this,
scale in the Z direction. So did,
Uh, how did you add the bullion on your,
on your menu, on the
Add-on? So
edit preferences, add-ons, bull tool.
If it's not available in here, go to get extensions
and look for bull B-O-O-L-T-O-O-L.
Okay?
Found it in extensions, Jesse says, wonderful.
Okay, just, just, uh, just to share a little bit for, so
for, uh, digital bodies week, my output were was tiny.
So this is me with a giant eye beams shoved through my body
that I use blender to do.
Uh, and this is me
heartless here, empty in the middle.
Okay? So this is, this was all done using the, uh,
Boolean operation that I'm about to show you,
uh, here.
Okay? All righty.
Okay, so I'm gonna take this beam and I'm gonna GZ move it.
Oops. GZ, huh? Select it first. Ricoh, okay.
Oh wow. Like, look, I just noticed
I loaded the skin after all.
I didn't think I did it, but there you go.
Okay, so GZ, move it up into the body.
Alright, so different operations you can do here.
So the bull tool offers two sections.
One of them says auto Boolean,
and the other one called brush Boolean.
I have no idea why they're using
these super confusing names.
But auto Boolean means that it will be permanent brush.
Boolean means that it can, it's sort of temporary.
You can play and see what it will look like.
So, okay, the first option for Boolean is different.
So if I take this object, select the cutting object,
hold down the shift key,
and then select my, uh, target object, which is the body,
and then hit difference,
it will generate a hole in my body like that.
Okay? And here's the fun part.
My cutting tool still remains so I can move it around.
So if I hit g ooh, I can move the hole around my body.
Remember yesterday there was like some,
some artist did something like this.
Okay? So let's move it here
and then let's make him faceless.
Okay? Now I have a hole through the face.
And this, this cutting tool can be scaled and move.
So I can scale it to make it smaller,
scale it in the X direction to make it more narrow.
Scale it in the z direction to make it taller, GZ
to move it down in the body.
So if you want to get artistic, there you go.
Okay. All right.
So if, uh, squares are too boring for you,
let's bring in a cylinder.
So shift A and we're gonna do
cylinder awfully big.
So we'll scale that down a little bit
and, uh, let's turn this guy into Frankenstein.
Frankenstein has these little
things sticking out of his head, right?
So GZ to move it up, um,
GY to move it forward a little bit.
Uh, okay, I'm gonna look at it straight on
by hitting the minus y button up at the top here.
Zoom in and rotate like this,
scale it down a little bit more, move it
to the right gx to move it to the right.
Okay, that's getting there.
And now I wanna do one on the other side.
And here is where modifiers comes in. Okay?
So I click on this object, I go to the blue wrench icon,
add modifier, generate mirror in the mirror,
uh, sort of settings.
There's a water droplet tool under mirror object.
If I click on the mirror, object droplet come over
and select my, my body, it will use that
as the center point for my object.
So now I have two horns on my
guy, so that's bullion.
Alright, so if I want to add these two things to my figure,
so I'll select that as my, uh, Boolean object, shift key,
select my final object, and then do union.
So now the, these, these two horns are now going to be added
to my object permanently, but also I have intersect, okay?
Intersect is interesting.
Uh, let's bring in another geometry.
Let's do shift A to bring in a UV sphere,
scale it down a little bit, uh, move it up GZ
to move it up GX to move it to the side,
GZ to move it up.
S to scale it down a little bit.
Okay, let's do intersection.
And this, this is going to generate a very bizarre result,
but let's just try it anyway 'cause uh, somebody asked.
So cutting object shift key body or
or target object intersect
and it leaves you with the, the part where the two objects
were interfacing with one another.
So we get this little snippet of ball and body together.
Okay? So that one is awful, so we're gonna undo and,
and get, so that's no fun.
And then the last one is slice.
Uh, so slice, uh,
as you can imagine is going to cut the object.
So if you for whatever reason want
to chop this body in half, uh,
or you want to create your own slicer, I suppose you can do,
I'm gonna do shift A and add a plane
and let's move this thing up, GZ to move it up.
Let's look at it straight on
and rotate it some crazy degree like that.
Um, and now I'm going
to click down the cutting object shift key
body object and slice.
I believe now we might have, no, it did not work.
I'm not, yeah, I'm not, I don't use slice very much.
I see a line in the body here.
Oh, I bet I know if we go to wireframe view, yeah, if we go
to wire frame view, we have some new, a new line here
that's generated by the slicing object.
Okay? So theoretically you could do your assignment this
week by doing a, a bunch of these planes and,
and using it to slice the object
and then exporting these, uh, uh, curves as SVGs.
Alright? How is everybody doing so far?
Is, is this, are you conf like, give me either a heart
and a lovely image or a skull
and bones if you hate what I'm doing
and you completely don't understand what's happening.
Good. Everybody's coming along for the ride. Just fine.
Wonderful.
Okay, so that's bullions.
That's, uh, make human, uh, let's make a torso.
Do you wanna build a snowman? Let's make a snowman.
Let's make a snowman. Why not?
Uh, not Anastasia gave us free.
You can use the, the sculpt tool.
Oh, I can't do sculpt.
If you wanna use sculpt, you can, and it's fun,
but, uh, i, I don't know how to use it,
but let, let's, well,
since the boss is asking me let's go there, it,
It's just exactly like the thing that I showed online.
I know, but I, it's Embedded in blender.
It's like making somebody who likes, uh, blue
wear a red shirt, you know, like I,
I just like, nah, I can't do it.
But in any case, uh, for those of you interested,
at the very top of the blender window is a
tab called sculpting.
So if you click on sculpting, you get a bunch
of new tools on the left hand side here.
So basically at the top here are workspaces, right?
Where you can do, uh, different things.
Wait, there's some stuff in the chat.
I found the extension actually is bullion for modifies.
Can you undo bullion unions? Ah, yes.
Uh, let me attack, do Claire's question first.
As I said before, I'm gonna go back to layout
so I don't be somewhere, none
of these objects have created a permanent, um, uh,
bullion on the body itself because I use brush Boolean.
If I had used auto Boolean, it would be permanent.
But right now, if I take this plane
and gx move it out of the body,
the body no longer has the hole inside.
Okay? 'cause I've never applied it.
And if I delete that plane, it's bye-bye forever. Okay?
If you want to apply it, you must go to the bottom here
and it says apply cutter.
If I do that, all of these sort of, uh,
extra rectangular boxes
and all this will disappear, then I'll go ahead and do it.
Oops. Error. Why? It doesn't like it. Why?
Why does it not like it? Uh, toggle cut cutter. Nope.
Oh, boy. It's giving me errors. Uh, let's do this one.
Apply. Cutter. Nope, it doesn't like it. Okay.
Something, something horrible has gone wrong.
Um, yeah, I'm not gonna mess with that right now,
but yes, you can undo by just simply, first of all,
you can control Z to undo anything.
Secondly, you can just take the cutter
and just delete it, uh, which is X on the keyboard
to delete and it's gone.
Okay? All right.
Now sculpting, uh, go to the sculpting workspace.
You've got a bunch of tools here.
I think the tool that is easiest to use is grab,
and I think in sculpting workspace, if I type G, yes, if I
to type G instead of move, I get grab
and you can, how do I change the brush size?
Uh, okay, the brush size can be controlled here.
I think there's a way to like,
um, hold on a second.
I'm gonna figure this out. Nope. Okay.
If you can use the radius thing here
to adjust your brush size.
So what did, what did, uh, Anas do?
She made a bunch of lumps, right?
Oh, so grab, Nope, that did not work.
Okay, let's try something else. Uh, what is this?
You can put a lot more strength.
Ah, strength, okay. Like a lot more. Yeah.
Yeah. One of the I want mask,
edit color filter cloth mesh.
Where's, where's grab? Oh, sorry, it's down here.
Uh, grab is this one. So why is it not working?
Oh, edit mode. Do I need to be in edit mode?
No sculpt mode
Actually in the modes.
Uh, if you go to the mode sculpt mode, yeah, that's it.
I'm in sculpt mode and it's not allowing me
to grab any of the geometry
And which object is active.
Okay, maybe nothing is. Okay, let's try this guy.
Nope, not happening.
Yeah, I, you guys are gonna have to play
with sculpt on your own.
Uh, I don't know how to use this tool
and it, um, it's not something that I'm comfortable with.
So please, let's leave it for now
and, uh, you guys handle that at another time.
All right. So we will, uh, hide our lovely,
distorted human for now
and all of the Boolean tools
that we've generated and this fall.
And we are now going to learn how
to model, oh, look at that.
Here's the slice that was generated
with the slicing, uh, Boolean.
So let's, where is that? I'm gonna get rid of that as well.
Uh, delete it. Okay. X to delete? Nope.
Okay, delete. There we go. All right.
So, uh, do a little bit of a stretch.
We're gonna do some modeling here. Okay?
First thing we're gonna do is add a cube.
Uh, the best way to this is called box modeling,
and it's a way that's very gentle for blender, meaning
that if you start with a cube, it doesn't have
so many subdivisions, so blender doesn't freak out and,
and, uh, it doesn't have to calculate so many things.
So shift A CUB enter gives me a cube.
I'm gonna, right now it's sort of like halfway
below the ground plane.
So I'm going to GZ and move, move this up a little bit.
It's going to become a torso. All right?
The first thing we're going
to do is apply a modifier to this.
So go with the object selected, go to the blue wrench icon,
add modifier, generate subdivision surface, okay?
Or, uh, subs.
Surf is a, you see that shortcut it or sub D
or subs surf, uh, we'll generate this.
So what it did was to take my cube and subdivide the faces.
So let, let me just show you the in edit mode.
If I go to edit mode now, right now
you have six faces, right?
But if I add the modifier,
I add the modifier, add modifier,
generate subsurface subdivision surface it, it's
splits each phase into four phases.
So four times six, uh, 24 phases, right?
Uh, but I have not applied my, uh, modifier yet.
So if I go hit tab to go into edit mode, you see
that it still thinks it's a cube,
even though it shows in the viewport as a subdivided object,
we're gonna use this unapplied object to create the torso.
Um, so first we're gonna create some new subdivisions
to this cube, and we do that with a loop cut tool.
So once again, all of my shortcuts are indicated here.
So we're, now we're gonna use loop cut,
which is control R or command R.
And if you move your cursor around, it's going to sort
of change its position as to
where it's gonna generate the cut.
I want a vertical cut in the middle of my object.
So you're gonna click once and then hit the escape.
Right Now it allows you to move your, uh,
loop cut left and right.
You don't want that, you want it
to stay exactly in the middle.
So hit escape to keep it exactly at the middle,
and then hit enter to accept that new loop cut.
So now my cube has a split
and in the middle, okay, uh, I'm going
to toggle x-ray mode.
So I can see through the object right now there's a,
a vertex hidden behind this cube here that I cannot see,
but if I do alt Z on my keyboard, it will make my
geometry sort of see through,
and I can see that, uh, dot in the back.
Okay, alt Z once again to toggle on and off X-ray mode.
And what I want to do is delete half of this object.
So I'm gonna left mouse click drag
and select all of these
dots from the left side to the middle.
I'm going to hit the X key for delete,
and I'm going to use faces.
I'm going to delete all of the faces on that half.
So f to delete the faces. So now I get half of the object.
Why am I doing this? I'm doing this
because I want to create a symmetrical object, right?
So this way I can model on one side
and it will also appear on the other side.
But in order for that to happen, first we have
to select hit A to select all, go
to my ad modifier generate mirror,
and it will create the other half for you.
Make sure every time you use the mirror modifier that you,
you check the clipping checkbox in the middle here,
or else you're gonna see some weird things happen.
So go ahead and click that, right?
And now you'll see that when I make a modification to
this side of the object,
it will also appear on the other side.
So as an example, I'm gonna grab this lower vertex here,
hit G on my keyboard, and I stretch it.
And you can see that it will distort in both directions.
Okay? So this is an easy way to, to, uh, manipulations.
Alright? So if this is going to be a body,
we are generally wider than we are in, in depth.
So what we can do is rotate it
or hit the x uh, button on the gumball over here.
Go ahead and, uh, drag, select the all
of the vertices in the back.
And because I'm still in X-ray mode, it's capturing all, uh,
four vertices in the back there.
Um, and hit G to move
and y to move it along the Y axis.
I'm gonna squish this to something like that.
So we'll start with that. All right,
so we don't have enough geometry
to do like the upper chest versus the lower body.
So we need to add a couple more loop cuts.
So control R one more time to add a loop cut.
This time before you do anything, roll your mouse button,
middle mouse button,
and it can, it will add extra subdivisions.
So I wanted div uh, subdivide it
vertically into three sections at the moment.
So do that. Once again, you don't wanna move this around.
So hit escape key to lock it in.
And now I have it subdivided vertically.
This way for the side.
I also want to add, uh, from front to back, I want
to add three subdivisions.
So control R to do loop cut, make sure
that it's in a vertical orientation.
Roll your mouse one time to do that.
Click escape key, and it's locked in.
So now I have a few more subdivisions to play with,
uh, front to back.
Uh, let's do the same thing.
Control R roll the mouse button,
click and escape.
And so now we have, it's subdivided this way.
Everybody with me so far except for heaven, who's driving?
Please don't be playing with blender while you're driving.
Good. She's nodding to me. All right.
New tool, uh, at the top of your screen, uh,
which I cannot get to because of my zoom thing.
If you type O okay, let, let, let me do something first.
If I go and, uh, look at my object straight on
by hi hitting the minus y key,
and I select the lower right corner of, uh,
my torso, it selects all
of the nodes all the way from front to back,
which is what you want.
And you see that if I wanna move this, like squeeze it
and create a waist and do GX, it will only move those,
uh, vertices that you selected, not the neighboring,
uh, vertices as well.
We don't want that, right?
What we want is when we move these vertices,
we want these vertices here
to also squish inward a little bit.
And the way we do that is by using the O key, which allows
for proportional editing.
When you type o, there's a little blue circle on the top
of your screen should turn blue.
Okay? And that now you know
that you're in proportional editing.
This time when I want to move this in the X direction gx,
you see a gray circle appear.
This gray circle is the circle of influence.
What, how much of the neighboring, uh, uh,
vertices are going to move when I move
the selected vertices?
And you can change the size of the gray circle by using
the mouse button on scrolling the mouse button on your wheel
so you can make it bigger or smaller.
So if I make it really small
and I do, uh, GX, it will not influence its neighbors,
but if I make it bigger, sorry,
GX and I make it bigger, it will influence its neighbors
and it will kind of squeeze it in alongside
of those that you selected.
So it makes a nice shape.
So go ahead and start manipulating your shape.
So I'm going to do, what I'm going
to do next is take select these vertices here,
look at this thing straight on.
I'm going to g uh, z move this up a little bit,
and then I'm going to scale it
inside a little bit
scale, okay?
And we get something that starts to look like a torso,
except it looks a little weird.
All right, I'm looking at my torso from the side.
Now, uh,
what I wanna do next is to squeeze the bottom, uh, notes.
In this time I'm going to turn off proportional editing,
hit o on my keyboard to turn it off, select all
of the bottom nodes type scale.
And this time we'll do it in the Y direction.
So we want it to just squeeze in the y direction
to have it come in a little bit.
Okay? So front to back, uh, in, in our body we have a bit
of a curve, right?
So we can do that by selecting these set of nodes here.
Make sure proportional editing is on again and do GY.
And I can push that to give my body a bit of a curve.
And already it's starting to look like a torso.
We're gonna push out the chest area a little bit.
Uh, select these nodes here, uh, GY I'm going to
decrease the influence of my proportional editing
and push that out a little bit like that.
Okay? So we have something like a torso.
I'm gonna leave it like that,
but I hope you see that it's a reasonably convincing torso.
Now I wanna add, uh, arms and a neck.
And we're gonna do that by changing.
Right now we are in the Vertex select mode, which is, uh,
done by doing the letter one on my keyboard.
I'm going to select the face next.
So I want to select three, go the face, select,
and now the faces will have
little dots in the middle of them.
I want to select this one in the middle.
And I, I will extrude it upwards, uh, to make a neck.
So click on that panel
type E on your keyboard for extrude,
and it's going to automatically assume that you want
to do it in the Z direction, which is fine with me.
And just start extruding it up
and you'll have a neck and it looks awful.
It looks more like a Popsicle stick than than a neck.
So what you can do now is type one to go back
to Vertex select mode, select this one
and shift, and,
and we can move it in the ZY direction a little bit, ZY,
and we can move it up and select the one in the back GY
and move it to the back a little bit.
And now it's starting to look more like a neck.
Uh, maybe take this one, shift this one,
and move it in the X direction neck.
Okay? Uh,
now let's do the same thing with the arms.
So three, to get back into face, select mode,
select the arm area and E.
And this time we're going to go in the Y direction.
And you can see that if I keep on going with this, right,
I keep on selecting this phase and EI can, I could start
and, you know, I hit escape to allow me
to, to go free.
I can start doing this, and then if I look at it straight on
R to rotate my plane of extrusion EI can, I can con continue
to create an arm out of this.
And similarly, for the head, if you wanna make a head,
you can e to go up again,
s to scale, and then e to go up again.
And you can start building something that looks like a head.
Okay, so not too many commands.
So far, we're using the G to move, S to scale,
E to extrude.
So all of these things are shown to you here.
Extrude, loop cut, uh, scale, rotate,
grab X-ray view.
Everything that I've been talking about is, is all here
for you to use.
Any questions so far?
For those of you who were afraid of blender at the beginning
of this, uh, tutorial,
are you feeling less fearful of blender now?
Do do I have a heart? Oh, yes.
Poor is a good a heart for Marissa. Thank you very much.
Can I ask some question? Sorry.
Yeah, sure. Um, I'm feeling, I'm feeling okay about it,
but I, I know Rhino, so I feel like that's helped.
But, um, my question is, you mentioned that, uh,
we have a limited amount of undue
and that we should you changers to 150.
I guess, do you think that that's something we're gonna have
to deal with in this project?
Like, do you recommend that we actually do this right now?
Or is that like more advanced?
Um, a good, a good question.
Uh, my, my friend, uh, Pablo in FabLab,
Leon asked me this question,
or actually he made a comment, which is
that when you're using blender, when you're modeling
with Blender, you kind of have
to think two steps ahead in your head of what you want
to do next, right?
So you're not just randomly going in here, taking this edge
and you know, extruding it, right?
Like you're, you're like, okay, I wanna make a neck.
How would I do that based on the
geometry that I have right now?
Which of these faces, which of these edges, which
of these vertices would I grab to move
or extrude in order to make the next thing?
And if you're doing that, the amount
of undos you're probably going
to need will be like three or four.
If you're just sort of randomly going out
and doing crazy things, then, then it's going
to cause you a lot more consternation.
But just, just for, you know, we started off
with a cube, okay?
We started off with a cube.
We added a bunch of subdivisions by doing loop cuts
to create more subdivisions within this shape.
And we just started stretching things here
and there in order to make it look more
and more like a, uh, torso.
Okay? Right now, I mean, none of you are gonna tell me
that this looks good, right?
It's very blocky and so on, so forth.
But check this out, if I go, um, right now, I just tab
to get back into object mode.
If I right mouse click on this object
and I go shade smooth,
it looks significantly better all of a sudden.
Okay? And when you export this for slicing, it's going to be
smooth, not, not jaggedy, like before.
So I can turn it off, I can go back to shade flat
and it looks like a low poly angular bit here,
but if I write mouse, click, shade, smooth,
everything becomes a lot more like clay.
Okay. I, I, did I answer your question, Claire?
Was that, was that convincing enough? Um,
Yeah, like, I think I definitely get the idea
that we should be kind of thinking in advance about
what we wanna do, I suppose,
because some of us are gonna be like playing with this
for the first time, and maybe we're not at that level yet
where we can think ahead.
So, well, um, do you think, like, like,
I guess, I guess the real, the real question is like,
how quickly do you use up all of those on Undos?
Are you as an advanced user finding
that like you're using up more on Undos when you're doing a
complicated project?
Or like, like, is it likely
that we will use them up if we end up playing
around for a little while?
I, I try not to get myself into a position where I have
to use more than 30 undos.
I have it there as a safety net,
but I, I try not to get myself there.
So one thing that I've failed
to do in the past 15 minutes is save my file, right?
So the first thing you wanna do right now,
if you've made anything, is save,
because it could crash any second.
And, and then you'll lose everything that you've done.
I also mentioned, Claire,
that you can do an incremental save,
which means you can save different versions of this thing.
So as your model gets increasingly complex,
I would do more incremental saves so
that you can go back like 50 steps, uh,
before you started doing, going crazy with it,
and then say, okay, at least you don't have
to go back all the way to zero.
You go back 50 steps
and then build from version four
of your model, if that makes sense.
Yeah. So incremental save one more time is
control alt s okay.
Or command option S for you Mac folks.
Alright, that is, uh, you know, we,
we didn't create a beautiful torso.
Uh, hopefully you, you see
how it could eventually get there if I go into edit mode
and continue to push and pull on the vertices
or add more loop cuts
or whatever to, to give this thing a little bit more
geometry to play with.
Okay? But I think I'm running out of time.
Have I run out of time? I think I've run out of time.
I do want to show you how to give this thing color. Okay?
So right now, if I go to render mode,
it's just a white blob, which is super uninteresting.
So with the object selected, we go to the bottom
icon in the properties window,
which is a circle, checkered circle.
We're going to click new to add a new, uh, material.
Um, what should we call this material?
I'm gonna make it, um, I'm going to make this a metal shiny
red metal torso.
Okay? So I'm gonna call it shiny red,
shiny red metal.
Okay? And then, uh, under base color, I'm going
to give it the color red and
below base color is a option for metallic.
I'm gonna crank this all the way up to one, uh, roughness.
I'm gonna bring all, all the way down to zero.
And as you can see already that it's like super shiny
and reflective already.
Okay, maybe a little bit too much.
I'm gonna bring roughness up a little bit so it's not,
so it's, it looks like aluminum or something like that.
Okay? So this is basics of, um, uh, adding materials.
One, one more time. Uh, I'm gonna do, go ahead.
So you can add another material
by clicking the plus key here,
but here, let me do that anyway.
So I'm gonna add, add another material new,
and this time I'm going to create a glass material.
Okay? The default surface treatment is principle B, SDF.
But if you click on that, you got tons of different options.
Again, if you have a weak computer, do not try this.
'cause it, it could be bad for your pc. All right?
But there's something called ggl, uh, glass, B, SD, F.
All right. So let, let me create a beautiful emerald, uh,
color for my object here.
Something like that. And you
wanna know what that looks like.
Right above the surface menu, there's a preview menu.
So if you go there, it, it gives you a ball
and it shows you what this material looks like.
So right now the roughness is 0.5, so if I take that down,
it's gonna become more like a crystal.
Okay? So it looks very much like a crystal now,
and I'm going to apply that to the middle of my, my, uh,
mannequin just for fun.
Okay? And the way you do that, so again,
if you're in object mode, you have to deal
with the entire model.
But if you wanna get to the features of the object, you have
to get to the edit mode.
So you do that by hitting the tab key.
Let's select, uh, go three for face select.
I'm going to select holding down the shift key.
I'll select this phase, this phase, and this phase.
I'm gonna go back to my material section,
select material two, which I should have renamed.
And then below the name here, there's an assigned button.
So I can do a sign.
So now that section of my model is going to be a crystal.
It's no longer red, it's a see-through glass crystal. Okay?
I go back to edit to object mode, right?
Any questions? Was that super kind of clear about how
to add a material to your object?
Yes. Anybody completely lost? I can do it again.
We're good. Alright. 'cause the reason why is
'cause I wanna actually render this out to, to, uh, show you
what this thing looks like fully rendered.
So before, uh, you know, before you do that, let me go ahead
and call this, uh, emerald, uh, so that I have that,
um, right, I need to do some settings, uh, to,
to make sure this comes out the way I want.
So once again, the very top properties
icon is the render menu.
Currently I'm in something called ev.
Ev is the simplest late lease taxing, uh,
render engine for blender.
And it gives you this kind of result.
But you notice that my crystal is not very crystally.
I'm not being able to see through it.
So to be able to see through it, I need
to use a different rendering engine.
And it's called cycles.
And once again, not for weak computers.
For strong computers only.
So you click on ev, I'm going to use cycles
and under device, it gives me an option of CPU.
Uh, but I'm going to go to GPU
because I have a GPU in my laptop, okay?
And already you can kind of see through the face it,
it's starting to be able to show through.
Uh, and then for render right now it's going
to do 4,096 samples before it gives you the final image.
We don't have a time for that, so I'm going to change that
to something very low, like 32 so that we,
I can show you in a reasonable amount of time.
In order to render an object, you need
to have a light and a camera.
Uh, thankfully we have that in our environmental folder.
I have an area light, and I also have a camera.
You may not have that. And to add a light, you simply have
to be in the modeling window, shift a
and that there's a light, uh, menu down here
where you can add point, light, sunlight, spotlight,
area light, and then you can play with it at your leisure.
And similarly, if you don't have a camera,
there's a camera button down here as well.
So shift A to add absolutely everything. All right.
This next bit, uh, is going to go a little fast
and you're going to be very confused.
Uh, but in order for me to render a view, I have
to create a, uh, camera view of this object.
So I like the way it's oriented right now.
Um, maybe we do it like this, I don't know.
Okay, I like it like that, right?
So I'm going to go to view align.
View align, active camera to view.
All right, so now my camera has moved over
and it's looking at my object.
In order to position my object nicely within the frame,
I'm gonna hit the end key one more time
to get my side panel to come out.
We're going to go to the view tab.
And there are two, uh, check boxes you need
to check under lock.
You're gonna check the two 3D cursor and camera view.
Once you've done that, you are able to zoom,
uh, in that camera.
Basically, you're controlling the camera now
and the camera is zooming in and out on your object.
Okay, so now we have a scene.
This is exactly the rendered scene.
In order to render this image, all you have
to do is do F 12 on your keyboard
or go up here to the top to the render menu
and render image.
Okay? And I made a mistake,
and then now you get to see my mistake.
So right now it's done 17 samples.
So this is what the finish render looks like.
And I had forgotten to turn off the other objects,
so the other objects came in and played in, in the thing.
So I'm gonna kill this image
and go back to my other objects in the asset folder
and click on the camera menu to get rid of them.
Although, which one is this? This guy's Cube two. All right.
And this time I'll do F 12 one more time.
Um, and the other objects are no longer being
rendered, okay?
The crystal is still not quite showing very nicely.
So what I'm going to do is I'm gonna move my light
so the light, the camera,
everything can be manipulated in the same way you
manipulate geo geometry.
So g for grab, I'm gonna move it forward a little bit.
Look at it from the side,
and I'm going to rotate it
so it points directly into my guy.
Maybe drop it down a little bit
and r to rotate,
point it at my guy, look at my guy from the front.
And rotate. No, let's look at it from the top
and rotate it a little bit at an angle GX to move it off
to the side a little bit to make it a little bit more sexy.
Uh, then back to some view that I like.
View align.
View align, active view to
align active camera to view.
Okay, so we're here. And once again, F 12 to render.
If we must download anything to have, um,
uh, to do the, the same like rendering
a program. Uh,
I'm, I'm sorry, Linda, I don't quite understand your
Question one more time. I think that we
must, uh, download any other program
to have, um, rendering or it's all in No,
No, no. This, this
is the beauty of Blender is
that the rendering engine is exceptionally powerful.
Uh, and, and it can do all its things.
So now you can see that the eye section here has a bit
of a crystally, uh, image to it.
I, I hope you can see that. Okay.
Uh, Rico, uh, if, uh, do you have other things
that you would like to, uh, mention?
Because me now I would like to close with a fusion?
Yeah, you can. I, I am done.
Uh, so the last section in my notion notes was using
modifiers and, uh, I've done most of it, maybe just one, uh,
wow factor thing to, to do, to show you guys,
I'm gonna unlock this thing.
Hit end to get out the tab, uh, hide my, my,
oops, hide this Mr.
Red robot guy. We're gonna bring in a new, make human dude,
uh, new human from scratch and create a new human.
Scale it up a little bit, okay? Oops.
Scale it down a little bit. Alright?
And lemme show you what a, what modifiers can do today.
So yesterday, uh, uh, Anastasio showed you some artwork
that was, took this object and turned it into a wire frame.
So once again, add modifier, generate, uh,
wire frame, all right?
And we get a wire frame object, and then you can go
and play with the thickness of the wire frame to change
what the object looks like.
Uh, I'm going to add a decimate modifier
to make this thing a little bit more arty.
Um, and okay.
Oops. Uh, oh, I think my computer's crashing. No. Okay.
Yeah, I don't, I shouldn't be doing this in rendered view.
That was the mistake. Okay, so anyway, there you go.
Instant art. And
to apply, uh, that shiny red uh, material to this, we go
to the material window
and you see that there's nothing there so far,
but we've already created red metal.
So I can go to this little white ball with the down arrow
and I go shiny red metal,
and it comes in as an option for this object now.
So when I go ahead
and go back to the rendered view, it's shiny red metal
'cause you've already made the material.
Okay. All
right, with that back to you.
Thank you very much. Hope that was helpful.
And, uh, look at the recording for anything
that I went too fast on.
I hope that was good.
Ready? Go. Thank you so much.
Uh, I hope that, uh, you will sleep very well.
I guess it is already one, 1:00 AM in the night,
something like that in Japan.
Thank you so much for taking the time.
Um, and it was great actually.
I, I have been using Rhino for
19 years now, but, uh, I am sure
because it's just everything is easier in blender.
Everything is just easier. You can do so quickly.
Um, anyway, I will, I will continue with the last, uh,
15 minutes just to show you the last part of the tutorial,
which is how to make the file to factory files
using the slicer for Fusion 360.
And yeah, I will continue.
Thank you, Rico.
So we've done our human in make human,
then we've done some modifications using,
uh, blender or whatever you want.
Actually, I did some modifications here, uh,
in this online browser.
But then after I opened the blender
and I did the bullion operations, uh, so,
uh, then I opened the slicer.
Slicer is brilliant.
It's, uh, it's an amazing tool and it has been discontinued,
but, uh, still works.
So I will, uh,
open from my computer
and it should be, man, um,
no, I will import, sorry, imports here.
Import
in my downloads.
And here it asks you which axis.
And if it is STL or OBG, I need to find it.
The search engine is very bad, so
I think it's called Man Cat.
Let's see.
Yeah, so I have edited with a scalping sculpting tool.
My, my figure,
and I cut ahead because the make human gives you a head
with a mouth open and a cavity.
And most of the time this is problematic.
So actually I open it with a,
a wrong directionality,
so I can rotate it like here.
Now, the first thing that I need to do is that I need
to go here, here into the manufacturing settings
and set up the laser cutting
machine dimension.
So, um, we can work
either in inches or in millimeters.
I will work in millimeters here.
I will create a new,
and it'll call, uh, laser cutter,
like laser cutter, um, 60
by 30, 600 by 300 millimeters
in millimeters.
And here I will put the dimensions of my laser cutter.
So 600 by 300.
Now the thickness is the thickness of the material
that you want to use.
You can add this here and,
or you can change it also later.
But I would pre, uh, recommend, uh, three millimeter,
uh, plywood.
And here are the margins.
And here is the slot offset, which means like
how much should be, uh, the opening so
that it's like the jog between the two pieces.
I leave it, uh, as it is, I don't, so
I will select now I saved my new board.
I will select it, and then I will go
and check the scale of my model
because I didn't, um, I, I didn't work, uh,
incorrect scale.
I need to put it back in the correct scale.
So I will make this,
if my board is 600,
I will make this 580.
So it will scale to the size
of my board, and then magic will happen,
which is actually, it's very interesting
because you don't know which side is up
and which side is down in this model.
But, uh, here you can select the different techniques.
So the easiest technique would be stack slices,
and you can, uh, go here and,
and play, and it'll
show you how to build it
in stack slices.
And then you can get the plants
zero.
Okay, so I need to make it smaller.
Uh, let's make it 400.
Yeah. And here you get all the boards
that you need to use for making this with a technique
of stacks, slices that you can export.
SDXF.
Now here in the get plans, these are all the plans,
but you can also change if you want the slice direction.
So you can use those rotating,
uh, accesses
and you can change the slice
direction to whatever you want.
This technique is called stack slices, meaning
that you will have always one piece.
Yeah, you can put here the angles 45
and you can put here the angle, for example, 13.
Yeah. But, um,
you have also more techniques like interlock slices,
and here it does this waffle structure.
Now we can actually,
uh, modify the slice direction
and reset it to, to be straight,
or we can turn it.
So you can turn the slice direction
and you can see directly, uh, if your pieces fit
on the, on your, on the board.
And you can also change the other direction as well.
Like this, for example, not every
red is bad.
In this case, yes, it is bad
because it goes out of the, of the laser cutter,
but not all the time.
What it shows. Red is bad. You need to to see it.
But this one, yeah, it doesn't fit.
The nesting is done, not done correctly. Here.
You can add more slices if you want.
You can grab them and move them.
So you can put them more dense
where you want to have more resolution and less dense.
You can add them from the bottom as well,
or you can can choose and delete.
You can make them even here again,
it's like resetting, or you can make them by count.
So then you have
curve, which basically
makes a curve if you do the slice direction
is just this curve.
So it'll, you make a,
it's very complicated.
This one make a curve
and it slides over the curve.
You see most of them are red here.
It doesn't work all the time, okay?
But you can play with that.
You have these points, so
more complicated, but it needs
to be played.
And then you have radial slices.
That's one that I quite like, I think.
So the radial slices there from here.
But if I change the slice direction
and I put this into 90,
you have it there in the middle.
And then you can also
rotate the, the center.
So this is radial, it keeps the center
and it goes around, which is nice.
And you can again, more, uh, add.
A nice thing is, uh, the folded panel.
Somebody was saying, I would like
to do more like folded origami.
You see, this doesn't work.
This one, you really need to work on this.
It's more complicated, this one
because you need manually to, uh, add
and remove the scenes according to your logic
how this thing can fold easily, you know?
So here I want this piece to be like that.
And the, the thick ones are the ones, um,
that is cut.
And the other ones, they're the ones that they're fault.
So blue is the one that works.
But for example, if I make this one piece,
it'll work as well.
Yeah, it should work done.
So normally it should become blue as well,
but it didn't, but it works.
This, eh, folded panels is very nice,
but you need to play a lot with the seams.
Um, I don't know if there are any. Yeah, okay.
Um, and then you just have
the 3D slices, which is, uh, basically stack slices,
but in 3D exports, like SDL.
So here you see the assembly steps.
It says you can choose the material if it's plastic,
carbo or plywood.
And then you just go and you see how to assemble it.
So, so you see
that the stack slices is the one
that takes most of the material.
Now, one other thing that it is nice
here in the stack slices, let's change the slice direction
and reset it so it's straight.
What you can do,
and I really like that you can modify the form
and you can make it hollow inside.
So here is how hollow, so how thick,
and you can apply this here, you can see on the side,
it'll take some time.
So get plants. Hmm.
Doesn't show. Hmm,
but here, normally it should be hollow, you see?
So it makes automatically the offset.
And you can also thicken it if you want,
or, uh, shrink wrap.
But the ho the hollow is the one that we mainly use
when we want to have the less
heavy material, let's say.
Or you want to put some lice inside.
So if you go, if you go to the interlock slices,
you see here that it is also
all red, but it would work then
after, what you would do
is that you would like that you download this.
So you need to get your plans here.
You can get them as DXF in the
correct scale, export to your computer,
and it'll export a zip file.
But what would you, you would like also is to optimize
a little bit the boards so
that you don't use so much material.
And this, you can do it manually.
You can open these files
and manually take this piece and put it here
because the nesting is not done, uh,
very perfectly in, in, uh, slicer,
it is done quite well, we can say, but not perfectly.
Um, but let me edit
this board because it is a very small laser cutter.
This one, I want to put it that this one meter
by 600.
Yeah. So now here you have only three boards
and you need to like have maximum five boards
that you cut it.
It'll be too much. Otherwise.
Here you can see the first thing you can need to do in
terms of fabrication is just to cut
a detail of two of those
and you can cut it
and see if they slide in easily.
They need to be sliding in easily,
but not doing like wobbly, uh, movement.
But they need to slide easily.
So this is very important
because if they don't slide easily
or they are too loose, you need to change
the slot offset.
So you can start with a default,
but here you can play with that so
that you can see which is the correct slot
offset for your material.
So the first thing that you will do in fabrication would be
to cut only two of those details
to see how they interlock.
And if they are interlock very, like very easily,
then you can go for it.
Otherwise, you need to adjust
this slot offset.
Hmm, I think that that's it.
Um, from that, apart from that, if you want
to try, because this operation, when
we do the placing
of the files on the board,
automatically it's called nesting.
If you want to try some automated nesting,
you can try Deep Nest.
It is an, uh, application that works quite nice
because you put everything in, you tell
how many boards you have,
and then it, uh, it'll try to calculate,
uh, your nesting.
It is better than the slicer.
Um, and the good thing is that it can, you don't need
to put board by board.
You can put all your pieces
and then it'll, you can put all the pieces
and the sizes of your, the boards that you have,
and then it'll generate automatically the boards
that you need to use.
So this is slicer. It is very handy.
We have been using it for many, many, many years,
and I hope that you can play with that.
If the things appear red on slicer,
put your logic and understand,
because sometimes they appear red,
but they still work,
eh?
Is it okay with the slicer?
Do you want me to explain something more? Or
Anastasia, when you were talking about utilizing deepness,
are we saving A-A-D-X-F file
and then taking it into deepness for adjustments?
Mm-hmm. Okay.
Yeah, the Deep nest is only for nesting.
The good thing of Deep Nest is
that you can put all the pieces and the sizes of the boards
and it'll generate many boards of how many unique.
But normally I don't use Deep Nest
after the slicer
because the slicer does already very good, uh,
job in the nesting
and I manually place in Inkscape, or
after I open another software,
I manually move them a little bit.
Uh, and, but you can try and compare if you, if you wish.
Um, Anastasia, can you explain,
so you put 580 millimeters, you said your bed was 600.
Was that just to give it a little wiggle room so
that it doesn't overset the bed
or what, what was the downs, the difference in those?
Yeah. Oh, very good question.
Uh, actually here, when you set your, uh, board,
you put the margins.
So if you want to have a five me five millimeter margin
all around, uh, the board, you can put this, uh,
to two actually.
Um, and here is the slot offset, which is the, the,
you know, the join.
So this is what you, I put it smaller, a little bit smaller
because I have noticed that sometimes it gets very confused.
Actually here now it is already confused with the direction
of my mannequin, and that's the reason why the, it gets out.
Like, uh, it takes out so many reds.
If I, um,
if I try to, you know, if I try
to import
and I put, uh, the why direction,
so it, when you open it, you should be able
to open it correctly
and standing like, um, here,
this is not correct.
No, uh, like the top view should not be this one.
So I will open it again or I will rotate it.
Yeah, the, no, this one I will just,
sorry, open it again.
I think it was already bad from the beginning
here.
Yeah, this is the back.
So this is the right, this is the front
and up.
So I should be looking at the correct view
front.
And this should be in my front.
Yeah, that would be better.
So here, normally what you need to do is you don't need
to arbitrarily scale.
You need to always work in the correct scale.
In the real scale. Uh, in this case,
because I put it in the blender, it is not in the co scale.
It's only 20, it is only 20 centimeters,
but in a model of a human torso,
half scale is 400.
If it opens like that, then you need
to modify the slice direction.
Sometimes this is confusing for the slicer,
but normally, yeah, yeah, if you look like this,
now you see here the pieces are huge
because I didn't select the correct,
um, board.
Yeah, this one is the correct board,
and here you see it's red,
but actually there is no reason for it to be read.
So, and the way that you understand this
is when you go into the assembly steps.
So you, you can view very well
what will go wrong in the assembly steps.
Again, this do in Yes. Do I have a problem up, up to now?
No. So for those, there was no reason for,
for them to be red.
Sometimes that's the problem in slicer,
but the, it can be red because it's too big or,
but everything works.
You can see it in the assembly step.
So I would use a little bit this scale,
but I would use the scale that you want the mannequin to be.
And you can see if it is just on the
borders of the machine bed,
then sometimes you get a lot of, uh, reds.
And that's why I put it a little bit
smaller, just to be sure.
But you can see everything in the assembly steps.
That's the nice thing. You can see the errors
and you can also try to use this hollow also
to see how it works.
Now one last thing,
because Marissa asked me, she said that she wanted
to do some more gummy stuff.
The, the, the interlocked, uh,
the folded panels here, I mean folded panels,
but I had a very curvy mannequin from the beginning.
I can use a modifier in blender
to triangulate the mesh first,
and then I can do the folded panels,
and then I can add, remove scenes, scenes like that.
And, um, but if you want to, if you're like really
into origami, you can, uh, see
Pura, Pura is a software for
origami, kigami, and folded panels.
It's incredible. So
it is not free.
So let's see. Yeah, these are the presets.
So, but uh, I've used it in the past
a lot and I loved it.
It's not free, but the student version
is only $30 to buy forever, I think.
And it is, man. Cut.
Let's see what we'll do with that.
Okay. Uh,
no flip finish.
So it could eventually,
uh, unfold.
Now it's thinking, but it could eventually directly unfold.
This, it is more precise than the folded
panels of slicer.
And again, you need to work with the seams and all of those.
Um, but this is, uh,
because Pepa is ex only, it's a software only for,
uh, for that, for, um, origami,
kigami and unfolding.
Do you have any other questions?
Both.
Well, thank you so much.
Um, I hope I, I am sure that it has been quite a,
a big load of information, uh, for everyone.
Uh, but uh, yeah, I hope that you will enjoy
trying out the different programs
and making your digital bodies.
Thank you. Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank.